<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The exhortation of Salomon. By H.A.</title>
            <author>H. A. (Henry Arthington)</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1594</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 137 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 35 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A21655</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 796</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S108342</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99844001</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99844001</idno>
            <idno type="VID">8780</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A21655)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 8780)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 167:09)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The exhortation of Salomon. By H.A.</title>
                  <author>H. A. (Henry Arthington)</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[72] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed [by T. Scarlet] for Cuthbert Burby,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1594.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>H.A. = Henry Arthington.</note>
                  <note>Printer's name from STC.</note>
                  <note>Running title reads: The exhortation to Salomon.</note>
                  <note>Includes, with caption title: A briefe praier of the foresayd text.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A-I⁴ (A1 blank).</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Sermons, English --  16th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2007-12</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2008-01</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-01</date>
            <label>John Latta</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-01</date>
            <label>John Latta</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:8780:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:8780:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>The EXHORTA<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>TION OF SALOMON. <hi>By H. A.</hi>
            </p>
            <figure>
               <figDesc>printer's or publisher's device</figDesc>
            </figure>
            <p>LONDON, Printed for Cuthbert Burby. <hi>1594.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:8780:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:8780:2"/>
            <head>TO The right Honorable George Earle of Cumberland, Baron Clifford, Lord Bromflet At<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton, Veſcie and Vypont, Lord of Weſtmerland, and Knight of the moſt noble order of the Garter,</head>
            <head type="sub">Together with the right vertuous Counteſſe his Ladie, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe of all bleſsings and graces needfull.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>S vngratefulneſſe for bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fites receiued, is a ſinne de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſted of God and man, (right honorable and my ſingular good Lord &amp; La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die) ſo ſtandeth me vppor more than anie other, euer to auoide that ſuſpition, &amp; to ſhew my thankfulneſſe both to God and his ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uants aboue all others, foraſmuch as I (being the greateſt ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner) haue notwithſtanding found greater fauour extended vnto me from the Almightie, my ſoueraigne Queene <hi>Eli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zabeth,</hi> her moſt honorable Councell, and all christian peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple,
<pb facs="tcp:8780:3"/>
in remitting of my late monſtrous offence committed in Cheape, and receiuing me againe to grace and fauour, more than euer was ſhewed vnto anie ſuch like ſinner ſince the world began. The remembrance of which moſt horrible fact, by me comwitted, as it maketh my heart and ſoule to tremble when I thinke ſeriouſly thereof, ſo my deliuerance cauſeth me oftentimes to breake out in thankfulneſſe vnto his goodneſſe, by whoſe onely power, prouidence and compaſsion, I was re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claimed from ſo groſſe errours, renued and reſtored to the vſe of my ſenſes, repriued from death and endleſſe deſtructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and reconciled againe into their former fauour, that ioye in the conuerſion of ſuch a ſinner, as hath bene ſubtilly ſedu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced by ſathan: ſo am I bound to intreate the Lords fauor, to recompence that vndeſerued kindneſſe a thouſaud folde into their boſomes, which I haue had from her excellent maieſtie, and all their Honours of her Highnes Councell, with all the reſt of Gods choſen children: which duetie by Gods grace I ſhall dayly performe ſo long as I liue, and more particularly for all thoſe to whome I am anie way more ſpecially beholden: Then my honorable good Lord and Ladie, ſeeing next her moſt excellent Maieſtie and honorable Councell in ſparing my life, I am moſt bounden vnto your Hh for the continuall maintenance thereof: her Ladyſpip mouing, and your Lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip conſenting to renue my Grant from your right honora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Father: yea, more than ſo, whereas I was both vnfit and vnable to diſcharge that office, wherewith I was charged by my Patent, your L. hath disburdned me of the ſame to attend better matters, and for thoſe grounds which I had in poſſeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, to allow mee one hundreth markes <hi>per annum</hi> during my lyfe, which fauor I acknowledge with all ſubmiſsion and vnfained thankfulnes, and as a further teſtimony thereof, do
<pb facs="tcp:8780:3"/>
humbly preſent this Treatiſe folowing vnto your Hh. as moſt fit, for two cauſes: The one in regard of the Argument ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, which firſt did ſpring from moſt honorable authors: the other in reſpect of my poore ſelf (who having taken ſome pains therein, to open the fountaine, that more plentie of wholſome water might flow from thence, to the comfort of others) your Hh. would bee diſpoſed to take the patronage of this ſecond fruit of my true repentance, intreating of the Exhortation of <hi>Salomon.</hi> As my former Seduction was both accepted &amp; allowed of their Hh. whom I had moſt diſhonored in my fall, when I was poſſeſt with the ſpirit of Satan, by that vile Sor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerer <hi>Hacket</hi> and his inchantmentes. To conclude, if your Hh. will vouchſafe to peruſe the ſame, and ſo farre only to ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proue thereof, as you ſhall find it to abide the triall of the true touchſtone, the word of God, I ſhall thinke my paines ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ently requited, and be more bounden to pray for your Hh. and all yours, whome the Almightie protect, preſerue and proſper with much increaſe of honor and comfort, both in this world, and in the world to come, A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men in Chriſt.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your Hh. obidient at commandement, <hi>Henrie Arthington.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:8780:4"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:8780:4"/>
            <head>
               <hi>To the chriſtian Reader encreaſe</hi> of thoſe eſpeciall grates, which may moſte further his comfort <hi>in Chriſt.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">B</seg>Eelooued in him, who looued vs moſte dearely when wee were all loſt: Jf you call to remembrance what I haue publiſhed in my pit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiefull Seduction, you ſhall finde from page 53. to the latter end of page 55. That J make mention of two ſortes of people, whome Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tan very groſlie ſeduceth: The one by alluring them to profeſſe poperie or ſome falſe Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on: The other to polute the true profeſſion, by a prophane and looſe conuerſation: of which number are all carnall Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pellers, promiſing in that place, that I will proclaime open warre againſt bothe and all other aduerſaries whilſt I liue. Since which time (and yet during my moſte iuſt reſtreint) I tooke occaſion to peruſe the holy Bible, to arme mee more ſtrongly againſt all ſuch enemies: and comming by courſe vnto the notable ſpeaches of <hi>Dauid,</hi> (which is the main ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument of this diſcourſe following) conſidering the ſame to contein ma<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ter of fit inſtruction againſt all papiſts and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phane perſons, and withall reuoluing my minde what neceſſarie doctrine I had once heard a Preacher of the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pel to produce publiquely out of the ſa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>e. I did foorthwith pre<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pare to indite and write what good matter I could conceiue
<pb facs="tcp:8780:5"/>
and gather out of the ſame, and ſo (by Gods helpe) did fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh without direction from any Perſon or any other meanes (ſaue my weake memorie and the booke of God du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring the time of my impriſonment) the which for ſome cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes (as a byrd vnfligge) hath hetherto lyen by mee, as vnfit to flie abroade.</p>
            <p>But now by the prouidence of the Almightie is permit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to be publiſhed for the vſe of ſuch as ſhall bee willing to heare or read the ſame, wherin the Lord knoweth &amp; bea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth witnes (that I ſeeke not my ſelfe) but his honour onely who hath preſerued mee, and their edification whome I haue offended any kinde of way: Jn which reſpect, J hope the courteous Reader will be are with the ſtyle (though for want of art or eloque<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce it ſeeme but harſh) for I profeſſe not learning, but plain dealing in all my indeuours, to profit ther by the ſimpler ſorte, which if by peruſing thou ſhalt acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, then haue I gotten my firſt requeſt. The ſecond is this, That as thou ſhalt feele it to chaunge thy minde and lyfe, to refourme either in any good meaſure, thou wilt not forget to giue God his due, the only prayſe of all, becauſe from him alone all good gifts proceede <hi>Iames</hi> 1.17.</p>
            <p>Namely for his extraordinarie fauour ſtill extended towards mee, in moouing all my good Creditors in London, to whome I ſtand deeply exdetted by ſuretieſhip, not only to remit mee all intereſts with charges, and to take their principalles onely at my handes after two ſhillings in the pound yearely till they bee ſatisfied, (If I liue ſo long:) But which is more, and ſo much as may be admyred of all men, wheras one of my creditors (vnt whome only I was a ſuretie, would not be pacified with his principall intereſt and charges at my hands, after the former rate for princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>palls only but either would haue it after twentie pound <hi>per Annum,</hi> or els my bodie ſhoulde lye in priſon. The which extremitie rather then my good creditors would ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer me to incurre: they haue all condiſcended to rebate ſo
<pb facs="tcp:8780:5"/>
much yearly of their due, to ſupply my want and ſatisfie his minde, whome mercie would not mooue (the Lord lay it not vnto his charge) neither forget to recompence their kindenes, that are ſo willing to extend mercie, as they haue learned of their heauenly father. <hi>Luke</hi> 6.35.36.</p>
            <p>To conclude I beſeech thee (good Reader) to pray for mee the Lords vnwoorthieſt ſeruant, that as my late fall, did bring to iuſt grief and offence to many: ſo my vpryſing by dayly ſignes and tokens of true repentance, may bring double ioy to all the redeemed that ſhall either heare or ſee the ſame. <hi>Amen.</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Thy vnfeigned wel-willer.</hi> Henry Arthington.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="summary">
            <pb facs="tcp:8780:6"/>
            <head>The ſeuerall diuiſions of the Text.</head>
            <list>
               <item>And thou Salo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon my ſonne, know thou the God of thy fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and ſerue him with a per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fecte heart &amp; a willing minde, for the Lord ſer<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cheth all hearts &amp; vnderſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>deth al the imagina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s of thoghts, if thou ſeek him he wil be found of thee, but if thou forſake him, he wil caſt thee off for e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer. 1. Cron. 28.9. Deuided into two partes.
<list>
                     <item>1 An exhor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to the true fears of God. Which is double. And
<list>
                           <item>1 Certaine circumſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces going be<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fore: Which are foure. folde.
<list>
                                 <item>1 Who gaue this exhor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation.</item>
                                 <item>2 To whom it was dire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted.</item>
                                 <item>3 When the ſame was gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen.</item>
                                 <item>4 Before whome.
<list>
                                       <item>The matter is double.
<list>
                                             <item>1 To know God And</item>
                                             <item>2 To ſerue his Maieſty.</item>
                                          </list>
                                       </item>
                                    </list>
                                 </item>
                              </list>
                           </item>
                        </list>
                     </item>
                     <item>2. Certaine ſound rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vnto. which are three folde.
<list>
                           <item>2 The ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hortation it ſelfe is dou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble alſo.
<list>
                                 <item>1 Touching the matter:</item>
                                 <item>2 touching the manner.
<list>
                                       <item>The manner double alſo.
<list>
                                             <item>1 With a perfit heart. And</item>
                                             <item>2 With a willing mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nde.</item>
                                          </list>
                                       </item>
                                    </list>
                                 </item>
                              </list>
                           </item>
                           <item>1 Is taken from the na<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>turall qual<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lities of god which is double.
<list>
                                 <item>1 That he ſearcheth all hearten. And</item>
                                 <item>2 That he vnderſtand all thoughts.</item>
                              </list>
                           </item>
                           <item>2 Is drawne fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe of god vppon con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition.
<list>
                                 <item>The condition: If thou ſeeke God,</item>
                                 <item>The promiſe: he will be found of thee.</item>
                              </list>
                           </item>
                           <item>3 Deriued from the iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice of god vpon iuſt oc<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>caſion.
<list>
                                 <item>The occaſion of Gods iudgement: If thou forſake him,</item>
                                 <item>The iudgement it falſe: hee will caſt thee off for ever.</item>
                              </list>
                           </item>
                        </list>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </item>
            </list>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="treatise">
            <pb facs="tcp:8780:6"/>
            <head>The Exhortation to <hi>Salomon.</hi>
            </head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>1. Cro. Cap. 28. verſe 9.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>And thou, Salomon my ſonne, knowe thou the God of thy father, and ſerue him with a perfect heart, and with a willing minde: For the Lord ſearcheth all hearts, and vnderſtandeth all the imaginatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s of thoughts: if thou ſeeke him, hee will be found of thee, but if thou for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſake him, he will caſt thee off for euer.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>ND all the whole Scripture of the olde and new Teſtament and euerie part and portion of the ſame: is writen for our ler<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning and further in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction in the fear of God (aſwel as for the Iewes) As Paul the Apoſtle witne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſſeth. Rom. 15.4.</p>
            <p>So amongſt many other no table places ſeruing to that end: this holy ſentence before alleadged doth conteine in it aſmuch varietie of excellent matter for mans obedience, (In my ſimple iudgement) as any text in all the Booke of God, bothe for the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter
<pb facs="tcp:8780:7"/>
and manner of his woorſhip, as in explaining the ſame ſhall manifeſtly appeare, if God ſhall be pleaſed to bleſſe my poor endeuour therin, which hath been and is my humble requeſt for the good of all people.</p>
            <p>To come to the woordes therfore, they ſeeme to deuide themſelves into two parts.</p>
            <p>The firſt is, A fatherly exhortation to the true feare of God, conteined in theſe woordes. <hi>And thou Salomon my ſonne, knowe thou the God of thy father and ſerue him with a true and perfect heart and a willing mind.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The ſecond expreſſeth certaine ſound reaſons to induce thereunto: videlicet <hi>For the Lord ſearcheth all hearts, and vnderſtandeth all the imaginations of thoughts If thou ſeeke him, hee will be found of thee: but if thou for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſake him, he will caſt thee of for euer.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Touching the exhortation, wee are more perticu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larly to conſider of theſe points.</p>
            <list>
               <item>Firſt, the circumſtances going before.</item>
               <item>Secondly the woordes of the exhortation.</item>
            </list>
            <p>Concerning the circumſtances, they be foure in number.</p>
            <list>
               <item>1 Who gaue the exhortation.</item>
               <item>2 To whome it was giuen.</item>
               <item>3 At what time.</item>
               <item>4 Before whome.</item>
            </list>
            <p>All which being opened, will bring greater light into the man or following.</p>
            <p>Touching the woordes of the exhortation they deuyde themſelues into two parts alſo.</p>
            <list>
               <item>Firſt, to declare the matter of Gods woorſhip:</item>
               <item>Secondly, the manner how to perfourme the ſame.</item>
            </list>
            <p>To come to the natures or ſubſtance of Gods wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip that is double alſo:</p>
            <p>Videlicet, <hi>To know</hi> (and) <hi>ſerue the Lord God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The manner is likewiſe two folde: that is to ſay <hi>with a perfect <gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>,</hi> and a <hi>willing</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>.</p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:8780:7"/>The reaſons to perſwade heerunto, are three folde euerie one more forcible then other:</p>
            <p>The firſt is taken from the naturall qualities pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per only vnto God, which is double, <hi>that be ſearcheth all hearts,</hi> and <hi>that hee vnderſtandeth all imaginations of thoughts.</hi> The ſecond is deryued from the promiſe of God vpon condition<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> the condition: <hi>Jf thou ſeeke God,</hi> the promiſe followeth, <hi>he will be found of thee.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The third and laſt reaſon, is drawen wholye from the iuſtice of God executing his iudgements vppon iuſt occaſion: the occaſion, <hi>If thou forſake God</hi>: The iudgement it ſelf, <hi>he will caſt thee off for euer.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Of all which deuiſions in perticulers, if I could ſet downe thoſe ſeuerall inſtructions that lye hid therin, then ſhoulde no man condemne my endeuour nor looſe his labour in peruſing the ſame, if with an hum<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ble and lowly ſpirit he marke what hee readeth: yet I wiſh all men firſt to try ere they iudge:<note place="margin">Iohn. 4.8.</note> for the ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit breatheth where it liſt.</p>
            <p>Now to ſpeake more largely of euery perticuler before deuided, and firſt concerning the Author of he whole, wee may finde by the ſtorye going be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, and by calling <hi>Salomon</hi> his ſonne,<note place="margin">Dauid the King gaue this exhor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation.</note> that it was <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uid</hi> the beloued king and propher of the Lord which dooth giue vs theſe inſtructions: So that if wee doe eſtimate of mens ſpeaches according to their places and ſpeciall iudgements: as if a learned man make an Oration, wee looke to heare it learnedly handled, or if a wiſe Magiſtrate ſhould giue a charge vnto the In rye in ſome mutter of great importance, wee looke to ſee it wiſely perfourmed: The how much more are wee to expect, that this exhortation proceeding from ſo wiſe, learned and holy a king (as the like ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer reigned either ſince or before in <hi>Jſraell</hi>) who was ſo deare in fauour with the Almightie, that he renu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ed with him the couenant of grace <note n="(a)" place="margin">Pſalm. 132.11, 12.</note> as out of
<pb facs="tcp:8780:8"/>
whoſe kindred, right ſtocke and lyne the promiſed Sauiour ſhould proceed: this muſt needes inſinuate that the exhortation following dooth conteine mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of great moment.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">2 Salomon the Prince, the par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie exhorted.</note>Concerning the perſon to whom it was directed it is plaine by the text, that it was <hi>Salomon</hi> ſonne and heire apparant vnto a kingdo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>e (though not by birth right) yet by the Lords apointment as hee <note n="(b)" place="margin">Gen. 25.23.</note> delt with <hi>Jacob</hi>: which muſt needes inferre the exhortati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on following to comprehend ſome notable matter, for who would once imagine, that <hi>Dauid</hi> both King and prophet ſo excelle<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tly qualified as we haue heard, would ſpend his ſpeach at any time, but to good pur<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>poſe, namely in his latter yeares labouring to inſtruct <hi>Salomon</hi> his ſonne.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">3 The time whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> this exhortation was giuen, viz. vpon DAVID his death bed.</note>To come to the very inſtant of time, when this ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hortation was giuen by <hi>Dauid,</hi> wee finde it to be a little before his ending, as wee commonly ſay vpon his death bed: and immediately after he had inueſted <hi>Salomon</hi> into his throne and kingdome in his life time to cut of all occaſions for <hi>Adonias</hi> or any other of his elder bretheren to chalenge the ſame after his death as appropriate to <hi>Salomon</hi> by the Lords election.<note place="margin">1 Cron. 28.5, 6,</note>
            </p>
            <p>This cannot but commend the exhortation fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing, for if we co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſider the courſe of all men, what perſon is amongſt ten thouſand, who hauing run ryot all his life time, and being arreſted with ſicknes vnto death, God giuing the partie grace to repent, but if hee haue the vſe of his wits with his toung to ſpeake will frame his talke to giue good counſaile to thoſe that are preſent?</p>
            <p>Oh then how much more ſurely may wee looke from <hi>Dauids</hi> mouth, for a wiſe, goodlye moſte com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortable exhortation, beeing choſen of the Lord, yea after his <note n="(c)" place="margin">1 Sam. 13:14.</note> owne heart, and now about to take his leaue and laſt farwell of this wretched world, withall
<pb facs="tcp:8780:8"/>
the pleaſure and treaſures therof, as his wife, Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, friends, lands libertie and life it ſelfe, who can I ſay (in reſpect of the promiſes) but expect the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hortation following to be moſt excellent.</p>
            <p>Now to proceeede vnto the laſt point touching the perſons, before whom <hi>Dauid</hi> exhorted <hi>Salomon,</hi>
               <note place="margin">4 The perſones before whome the exhortation was giuen. viz. the whole aſſem<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>blie of Duids Nobles. &amp;c.</note> the woordes precedent before our text ſaith, it was in the preſence of all his Nobles, ſending for them as ſemeth of purpoſe to be eye and eare witneſſes vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to his counſaile and laſt ſpeeches to <hi>Salomon</hi> his ſonne the rather to put him in continuall remembrance to practiſe the ſame after his death this muſt needs il<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luſtrate the exhortation following to bee woorthye the noating of all eſtates and callings, for the better manifeſtation whereof, it ſhall not bee amiſſe to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peat <hi>Dauids</hi> woords co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cerning the great aſſembly of all eſtates, before whome hee exhorted <hi>Salomon,</hi> which are theſe: <hi>Dauid</hi> aſſembled all the Princes of <hi>Iſraell,</hi> the Princes of the Tribes and the Captaines and the bands that ſerued the king and the captaines, and the ruters <note n="(d)" place="margin">1 Cron. 28.1.</note> of all the ſubſtance and poſſeſſion of the king and of his ſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nes with the Euunuches and the mightie and all the men of power vnto <hi>Ieruſalem,</hi> As it were calling an high Court of parlament of all Eſtates: how greatly dooth this importe that the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hortation muſt needs conteine mater of greateſt im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portance, to make the ſame knowen vnto all his E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtates, before God called him out of this world.</p>
            <p>But if wee ſhall ſearche a little further, into the manner and behauiour of this good King before all his Nobles, ere hee began to vtter theſe ſpeaches, it is ſaid, <note n="(e)" place="margin">1 Cron. 28.2.</note> that <hi>Dauid</hi> ſtoode vp vpon his feet and ſpoke as followeth, heare ye my bretheren and my people: preparing them all to a reuerent attention to heare that which followeth, and ſo after ſome generall
<pb facs="tcp:8780:9"/>
ſpeaches vſed to them all concearning his purpoſe touching their gouernment: by and by hee directeth his ſpeaches to <hi>Salomon</hi> his ſonne, as the moſte hono<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rable perſon in preſence, to mooue them the more to marke his ſpeches, ſeeing they all knew that <hi>Salomon</hi> ſhould ſucceed <hi>Dauid</hi> in his kingdome.</p>
            <p>So that if wee remember all the circumſtances of time, place and perſons, by whome, to whome, and before whome, with all other accidents before the exhortatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, we cannot but expect that it wil prooue as godly, as graue, as learned and excellent, as euer proceeded from the mouth of <hi>Dauid.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>O then conſider, ſeing we haue heard ſo many nota<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble and heauenly ſentences recorded and regiſtred in the holy Scriptures, of <hi>Dauid</hi> the King and Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet of the Lord. As in the bookes of <hi>Samuel,</hi> of the <hi>Kings,</hi> of the <hi>Cronicles,</hi> but cheifly in the <hi>Pſalmes</hi> and ſundry other places, which approue him ſo graced with all kinde of good gifts for his place and calling, as the like King was neuer in <hi>Jſraell (Chriſte Ieſus</hi> ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepted) how ought theſe reaſons to rouſe vp our at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tention to marke that which followeth.</p>
            <p>Now let vs heare the exhortation is ſelfe. <q>And thou <hi>Salomon</hi> my ſonne, knowe thou the God of thy Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and ſerue him with a perfect heart, and a willing minds, &amp;c.</q> What mortall man could giue better counſel, concerning the dutie of all degrees in ſo few ſpeches? In which graue aduice, directing the ſa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>e firſt vnto <hi>Salomon,</hi> he doth inſinuat thus much in ſubſtca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>e.</p>
            <p>
               <q>O <hi>Salomon</hi> of all the ſonnes that God hath giuen mee, (as I haue had diuers and elder then thy ſelfe ſince I came to my kingdome) yet to thee (abooue the reſt) haue I borne the greateſt looue, and for thee chieflye haue I prayed to my God, that thou mightſt ſucceede mee in my kingdome, wherof al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>readie
<pb facs="tcp:8780:9"/>
I haue put thee in poſſeſſion, and doe pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liquely pronounce before all my Princes: that it is the will of God ſo to haue it, and that thou ſhalt buylde an houſe <note n="(f)" place="margin">1 Cron. 28.5, 6</note> for his worſhip: Now therfore my deare ſonne, ſeing thou art preferred to this hie prerogatiue of Gods only fauour and mere mercie, and that I am going the way of all fleſhe, with full aſſurance to ryſe againe to glorie, heare now the laſt woordes of thy father <hi>Dauid,</hi> that euer her is lyke to ſpeake to thee in this world being ſuch as tende moſt for thy honour and comfort, looke thou learn therfore to make good vſe of them, euen to knowe and ſerue the God of thy Father:</q> what heart ſo hard (if it were not of flint) but would haue relented to heare ſuch woordes vttered from ſo woorthye a Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, as was annointed the Lords kingly Prophet?</p>
            <p>The Introduction into the matter being ſpoken off, let vs now proceede to intreate more plainly of the exhortation it ſelfe following, which conſiſteth of two partes, <hi>to knowe and ſerue God: Dauid</hi> ſaith not to <hi>Salomon</hi> know thy God only, and goe no further:<note place="margin">Marke this<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> knowledge and practice, muſt ioyne together in a Chriſtian.</note> or ſerue thy God, and leaue out knoweledge: but knowledge and obedience muſt bothe ioyne toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, in the true woorſhip and ſeruice of God: Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holde then what heauenly doctrine, for our inſtructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on doth lye in the entrance of this exhortatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, which in foure woordes dooth comprehend the whole ſub<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſtance of chriſtian Religion <hi>videlicet,</hi> To knowe and ſerue God, or to ſerue God according to knowledge, in which ſhorte ſentence this coniunction <hi>And</hi> is to be noted, and in all ſuch like phraſes obſerued, for it commonly ioyneth either two vertues or vices to<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gether, for the further explaining of the Lords will: As where hee ſaith, <hi>Hee that heareth my woordes and dooh the ſame I wil liken him to a wiſe builder<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </hi> and again,<note n="(g)" place="margin">Mat. 7.24</note>
               <pb facs="tcp:8780:10"/>
               <hi>Bleſſed are they that hear the woord of God and</hi> 
               <note n="(h)" place="margin">Luke. 11.28.</note> 
               <hi>keep it.</hi> Again <hi>Woe be to them that call euil good</hi> 
               <note n="(c)" place="margin">Iſay. 5.20.</note> 
               <hi>and good euil.</hi> with a number ſuch like ſentences recorded in the Scripture for our warning and inſtruction.</p>
            <p>And if wee marke well the force of <hi>Dauids</hi> ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches, exhorting <hi>Salomon</hi> to knowe and ſerue his God, wee ſhall finde his mynde and meaning thereby, to confute and condemne two ſortes of ſinners, that ſhould after his tyme ryſe vp in the world.<note place="margin">Two ſortes of ſinners reproued</note>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">1 All carnal goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pellers.</note>The former ſorte, doe bragge and boaſte much of their knowledge in Gods woord, but haue no care to frame their liues therafter, whome wee call Liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tines or carnall Goſpellers.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">2 All popiſh pro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>feſſors.</note>The latter on the other ſide, take pleaſure in do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing but at no hand as God requireth of them, and ſuch wee call all popiſh profeſſors ot profeſſors of po<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>perie, who make their owne wills a lawe in Gods woorſhippe.</p>
            <p>But to lay open both theſe kynde of ſinners to the view of all men, of the former ſorte are all ſuch per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons of what calling ſoeuer, as will be accounted pro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>feſſors of the Goſpell, and perhaps haue it on their tunges endes, but not in their hearts where it ſhould be lodged,<note place="margin">A carnall goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peller deſcribed.</note> to rule and refourme their liues therafter. As <hi>Dauid</hi> vſed <hi>Pſal. 119.11.</hi> for caſt your eyes a lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle into their proceedings how they cary themſelues in their conuerſation: and you ſhall finde ſome of them common prophaners of the Lords name, and Saboths: ſome diſobedient to their parents and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters,<note place="margin">The vnſauerie frutes of manye goſpellers.</note> and ſuch as be lawfully pla<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ted ouer them: ſome are malitious and wickedly minded, ſome are licen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious giuen to vncleannes, ſome are beaſtly <hi>Epicures,</hi> delighting only in ſurfeting and drunkennes, ſome giuen to their pleaſures, ſtage playes and ſuch like, ſome are ambitious or vain-glorious perſons, ſome
<pb facs="tcp:8780:10"/>
are verie couetous and mercileſſe perſons, ſome are extorting fraudulent perſons, ſome giuen to lying, ſwearing and blaſpheming, ſome to backbyting, ſla<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dering and ſuch lyke, all which make Religion no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but table-talke, or vſe it as a cloake to couer their filthienes.</p>
            <p>But let all ſuch perſons knowe and learne thus much,<note place="margin">Who are vain goſpellers and woorſhippers in vaine.</note> that except their liues and conuerſation be an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwerable vnto that Goſpell which they ſo much talk of, ſo as their practiſe agree with their profeſſion, and bothe be guyded by the rule of Gods word, in vain doe they bragge of the name of Goſpellers: Nay the greater ſhew they make of the ſame, and the leſſe they regard to frame their liues therafter: the greater and more ſharp ſhall be their Iudgements: for ſo the Lord Ieſus him ſelf ſaith: That Seruant that knowes his maſters will and dooth it not <note n="(k)" place="margin">Luk. 12.47.</note> hee ſhall be bea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten with many ſtrippes, for as without the light of the Goſpell of Chriſt, no man can ſee how to walke to pleaſe God, ſo vnleſſe all men bee as carefull in their liues to followe that light as <hi>Dauid</hi> 
               <note n="(l)" place="margin">Pſal. 119.105.</note> did, profeſſe what they pleaſe, it is to no purpoſe: for pure religion and vndefiled, as the Apoſtle <hi>James</hi> deſcribeth the ſame, <note n="(m)" place="margin">Iames. 1.27.</note> is to keep a man vnſpotted of the world: for not euery one that ſaith (<hi>Lord, Lord</hi>) ſhall inherit his kingdome, <note n="(n)" place="margin">Math. 7.21.</note> but thoſe that withall obey holy will.</p>
            <p>It ſhall be good therfore for euerie chriſtian to fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low Chriſts counſaile whilſt wee haue the light to walke <note n="(o)" place="margin">Iohn. 3.21. &amp; 12.35, 36.</note> after the light, that wee may become the children of light and ſo with Chriſt inherit his glory. Thus much at this preſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t againſt all thoſe bad kinde of people, that would be taken for great profeſſors and yet by their liues prophane all religion, practi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing thoſe things which are vngodly,<note place="margin">Good aduice to carnall goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pellers.</note> their ſoules and
<pb facs="tcp:8780:11"/>
conſciences witneſſing the ſame: to the great diſho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour of almightie God, and the like diſcredit of his glorious Goſpell: beſides the daunger of their owne ſoules, vnto whome I wiſh from the bottome of my hart (that as they ſeem religious in ſhew, and would be ſo accompted of others) they would become do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers of the woord<note n="(p)" place="margin">Iames. 1.22</note> and not hearers only, deceiuing their owne ſoules. Now let vs come to the latter ſort of people that haue ſo great a minde ſtill to be doing and yet refuſe to bee guided therein by the light of Gods woord: If a man ſhould aske a deuoted papiſt what kinde of good woorkes they make moſt accou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of,<note place="margin">The Papiſts good woorkes.</note> they will anſwere, to ſay and ſing maſſes, for the quick and dead, to go on pilgrimage, creeping to cro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſſes, cenſing of Images, building of monaſtaries, pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to ſaints, and for the dead, ſinging and ringing for ſoules departed, procuring of popiſh pardons and in dulgences, with their ouerplus woorkes of ſuperro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation, to purchaſe an higher place in heauen for the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſelues and their friends: he neither can nor will aun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwere directly that theſe woorkes are enioyned by the law of God, for they all knowe right well that there is neither commaundement nor example of a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny ſuch expreſſed in Gods woord but the flat con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trarie: If one demaunde further then, why they vſe them?<note place="margin">What opinion Papiſts holde of their Church &amp; the ſcriptures.</note> they wil ſoone reply, by the church comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dement, which they account to bee aboue the ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, wherof they holde ſo baſe an opinion that to be altogither ignorant therein, they tearme the mother of deuotio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> and ſo the more ignora<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t the more deuout.</p>
            <p>How wel all theſe points agree with the Scripture concerning their perticulers, marke what followeth and firſt touching the Church: we will obſerue theſe foure points chieflie.<note place="margin">4 ſpecial points of the Church.</note>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1 Firſt, what the Church is called and whereof it
<pb facs="tcp:8780:11"/>
conſits.</p>
            <p n="2">2 Secondly, wherupon the Church is compact and builded.</p>
            <p n="3">3 Thirdly, by whome and what lawes ſhe muſt be gouerned.</p>
            <p n="4">4 Fourthly, Whether thoſe lawes may bee truely ſaid to be abooue the Church, or the Church aboue them: All which points beeing rightly conſidered, will plainly decide this troubleſome controuerſie, betweene vs and the papiſts, touching the authoritie of the Church.</p>
            <p>To come to the firſt point,<note place="margin">what the church is called.</note> the Church is called the houſe<note n="(q)" place="margin">1 Tim. 3.15.</note> of God the ſpouſe<note n="(r)" place="margin">Epheſ. 1.22. Reuel. 21.9, 10.</note> of Chriſt the tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple<note n="(s)" place="margin">1 Cor. 3.16.</note> of the holy ghoſt conſiſting only of true belee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing<note n="(t)" place="margin">1 Cor. 3.16.</note> chriſtians in his woord, whome we common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly call the <hi>Church-millitant,</hi> to diſtinguiſh it, fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the triumphant, and from that houſe of ſtoane and timber appointed for the place of Gods woorſhippe which then was called the Temple of God.</p>
            <p>Shee is alſo called Catholique or vniuerſall, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe ſhe containeth the complet number of all faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full Chriſtians in all ages, and of all callings through out the whole world.</p>
            <p>She is alſo called <hi>one,</hi> becauſe all her members are of one faith <note n="(v)" place="margin">Epheſ. 4.4, 5, 6. 1 Cor. 14.33.</note> one religion, one heart and of one minde, to woorſhip and ſerue God after one rule, which is his bleſſed woord.</p>
            <p>She is alſo called <hi>holy,</hi>
               <note n="(x)" place="margin">Iſay. 4.3, 4. Act. 15.9.</note> becauſe ſhe is purified by the bloud of Chriſt, and ought to be <note n="(y)" place="margin">1 Pet. 1.15.</note> holy as hee her Lord is holy.</p>
            <p>She is alſo called the <hi>Piller</hi> 
               <note n="(z)" place="margin">1 Tim. 3.15.</note> ground of trueth be<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cauſe ſhee dooth not onlye profeſſe the trueth but ought to witnes and vpholde the ſame <note n="(a)" place="margin">Ephe. 5.23, 24.</note> ſo farre as the woord of Chriſt her hed dooth teach her, either for religion or conuerſation.</p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:8780:12"/>
               <note place="margin">2 Whervpon the Church is buil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded.</note>To ſpeake of the ſecond point whereuppon the Church is co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pact and builded, the Scripture beareth witnes, that the church is builded vpon the doctrine <note n="(b)" place="margin">1 Pet 2.4, 5. Ephe. 2.20.</note> of the Prophets and Apoſtles, <hi>Chriſt Jeſus</hi> being the hed corner ſtorne: for the ſame ſcriptures that doe witnes the calling of <hi>Abraham: Iſac</hi> and <hi>Iacob</hi> and all the reſt of his choſen ſeruants, whome <hi>Peeter</hi> cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth a royall preeſthod and kingly nation, <note n="(c)" place="margin">1 Pet. 1.23. &amp; 2.9.</note>regene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate and renued by the immortall ſeede of Gods ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cred woord, thoſe places doe witnes, that the Church of Chriſt is built on his woord: for otherwiſe they had not been called.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">3 By whome and what lawes the Chruch is to be guided.</note>Concerning the third point, by whome and what lawes the Church is to be ruled, that is very manifeſt (according to the ſcripture) by the Lord <hi>Ieſus</hi> and his onlye ordinaunces: for ſeeing hee alone is her Lord, husband, head, king and Gouernour, preſeruer and protectour, vnto whom all <note n="(d)" place="margin">Math. 28.18.</note>power in heauen and earth is ſubiect: It ſhould derogate to much from his honour and glorie, to haue the Church his ſpouſe guided and gouerned by any other lawes and ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances then by his only: <note n="(e)" place="margin">Iohn. 10.4.5. &amp; 16.13.14</note> neither will his choſen heare any other.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">4 Whether the Church or ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture muſt be ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueraigne.</note>The fourth and laſt point, which is the maine ground of the whole controuerſie, videlicet, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther thoſe lawes and ordinances which Chriſt hath commended and co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maunded in his woord, are a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boue the Church, and ought to direct her in all mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters touching religion and conuerſation, or that the Church is aboue the ſcripture, and may choppe and chaunge the lawes and ordinances of Chriſt Ieſus at her pleaſure.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Sundry reaſons that the Church is to be euer di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rected by the ſcripture.</note>The anſwer is plaine (by many reaſons) that Chriſt and his ordinances muſt ouer rule the Church in all <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſon. </seg>1</label> things. The firſt, if the lawes of Princes ruling by
<pb facs="tcp:8780:12"/>
Iuſtice, ought to be receiued, profeſſed and practi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed of all their ſubiects, much more the Church, ought to bee gouerned by the Lawes of Chriſt her Lord and king.</p>
            <p>Secondly, if the lawes and ordinances giuen by <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes,</hi>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſon. </seg>2</label> who was but a ſeruant, might not bee abrogate, chopped or chaunged of any mortall creature with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out <note n="(f)" place="margin">Deut. 17.26. Gal. 2.10.</note> the diſpleaſure of the Almightie, much leſſe then thoſe lawes and ordinances of the Lord Ieſus being the chiefe Lord and ruler ouer all.</p>
            <p n="3">3 Thirdly, when Chriſt gaue commiſſion to all his <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſon. </seg>3</label> Apoſtles to preach and teach all people and nations: hee left them not libertie to preach what they liſt, their owne traditions or vain inuentions: but what ſoeuer him ſelfe before <note n="(g)" place="margin">Math. 28.20.</note> had taught and com<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>maunded.</p>
            <p n="4">4 Fourthly, if Chriſt Ieſus only be Lord, head and <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſon. </seg>4</label> huſband vnto his Church (as none of the aduer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaries dare deny) then it followeth, that hee beeing aboue his Church, (as the head ouer the members) muſt needs rule ouer her by his owne lawes and or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinances:<note place="margin">The Papiſt opinion of the church aboue the ſcripture, quite ouerthrowne.</note> except they holde (againſt reaſon and gods law) that the members ought to ouer rule the head, or the wife the husband: &amp; ſo haue you this groſſe o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the papiſts, that the authoritie of the church to be aboue the ſcripture which is the law of Chriſt her head quite ouerthrowen as deuiliſh and damna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble: But the Papiſts may reply and obiect vnto mee,<note place="margin">An obiection.</note> that ſome lawes and ordina<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ces preſcribed by Chriſt, and expreſſed in his woord (euen within the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſe of the new Teſtament) were ſoone after ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rogate and diſſolued, therfore thoſe ordinances ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed in the woorde are not perpetuall, and ſo can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not rule the Church in all ages.</p>
            <p>To this I anſwere and graunt the preſident,<note place="margin">The aunſwer.</note> but
<pb facs="tcp:8780:13"/>
deny the conſequent,<note place="margin">What offices temporary.</note> for the Lord Ieſus ordeyned ſome callings in the Church to be but temporary as Apoſtles, Prophets and Euangeliſts, which could not continue in the Church for euer, becauſe they were onelie extraordinarie callinges for the firſt gathe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring together of the Church in all kingdomes, after Chriſts aſſention: But he ordained other lawes and offices,<note place="margin">What kinde perpetuall.</note> to be as ſtanding and perpetuall ordinances for the continuall inſtructing and gouerning of his Church and choſen people vntil his ſecond comming as appeareth plainly <hi>Rom. 12.4.8 1 Cor. 12. Eph. 4.8 13.</hi> and therfore may at no hand be altered, chopped or chaunged by any mortall creature, without ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſt rebellion againſt the Lord Ieſus.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">An other obie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction.</note>The papiſts being driuen from the former ſtarting hole, by and by they retyre into an other, and reaſon thus for the authoritie of the Church: the Church cannot erre, therfore ſhee muſt needs bee aboue the Scripture.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſwer. </seg>
               </label> To this may be aunſwered, that if it ſhould bee graunted the Church could not erre, yet it follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth not, that ſhe were abooue the ſcripture: vnleſſe they holde that the Scripture may erre, which is an abſurde moſt damnable doctrine, that the ſcriptures giuen <note n="(h)" place="margin">2 Tim. 3.16.</note> by inſpiration from God can erre in any point, which were to accuſe Gods ſonne of error.</p>
            <p>But let vs ſee how trimely they prooue that the Church cannot erre:<note place="margin">An other obie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction.</note> they ſay God hath promiſed vn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>to his church, to ſend his holy ſpirit to lead and guide her into all trueth, which he perfourmed when hee ſent the holy ghoſt in <note n="(i)" place="margin">Acts. 2.3, 4.</note> clouen tounges immediat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly afrer Chriſts aſſention, vpon his Apoſtles and cho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſen diſciples, therfore the church cannot erre, which they transferre to the Church of Rome, as peculier only vnto her holines.</p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:8780:13"/>So long indeed as the Church is guided by Gods ſpirit ſhee cannot erre, becauſe his ſpirit cannot erre:<label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſwer. </seg>
               </label> but when ſhe is not led by the ſpirit of God, ſhe can not but erre, for the want of Gods ſpirit, is the roote of all errors: therfore if they will rightly diſcearn be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween theſe two points and prooue that their church of Rome cannot erre: they muſt make it plaine, that her doctrine and gouernment is and hath beene alwaies guided by Gods ſpirit which cannot be iuſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied, but the quite contrarie in manner following.</p>
            <p>That Church which refuſeth to be guyded &amp; go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerned by Gods woorde in all thinges,<note place="margin">The firſt ſillo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſme to prooue the Church of Rome to erre.</note> that church is not euer lead by Gods ſpirit, and ſo muſt needs erre: but the Church of Rome re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſeth to bee guided and gouerned by Gods worde in many thinges, therfore ſhee is not al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waies lead by the ſpirit of God, and ſo muſt needes erre.</p>
            <p>The firſt part or maior of this propoſition: that the woord and ſpirit of God are inſeperable compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions cannot be denided, for the one hath alwaies re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation to the other: and therfore our Sauiour Chriſt when hee promiſed to ſend his ſpirit the comforter vnto his Apoſtles leaſt they ſhould bee deluded by the ſpirit of error, hee giueth them a ſure marke how to know the holy Ghoſt: When hee co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>meth (ſaith Chriſt) hee ſhall not ſpeake of himſelf, but whatſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>euer hee hath heard <note n="(k)" place="margin">
                  <p>Iohn. 14.26 &amp; 16.13, 14. &amp; 17.17.</p>
                  <p>Mat. 28.20. Iohn. 20 31. Marke this.</p>
               </note> and receiued of mee, that ſhall hee ſpeake and teach vnto you: for hee is the ſpirit of trueth, who ſhall bring vnto your remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance whatſoeuer I haue taught and commaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded you, and thoſe things are ſufficient vnto life e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternall: ſo that the ſpirit of God dooth alwaies ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peale to the holy ſcripture for her approbation.</p>
            <p>The latter part or minor of this propoſition that
<pb facs="tcp:8780:14"/>
the church of Rome muſt needes erre I proue thus:<note place="margin">The ſecond ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument.</note> That church which techeth other points of doctrine touching faith and religion, which is not approoued by the holy Scripture, that church muſt needes erre.</p>
            <p>But ſuch a one is the church of Rome: and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ſhee muſt needes erre. &amp;c.</p>
            <p>The maior part of this propoſition is proued be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore.</p>
            <p>The minor or latter part, that the Church of Rome teacheth certaine pointes of faith and Religion, not warranted by Gods woord, is thus prooued.</p>
            <p>That Church which teacheth that her authoritie is abooue the Scripture, that ſhe cannot erre in mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of doctrine: that in the Church bee ſeuen ſacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments: that prayer to ſaints and for the dead is law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full: that there is a purging place for ſinne after this life, before a man can get into heauen: that to goe on pilgrimage, to pray before Images, and to creep vnto croſſes are good woorkes that pleaſe God, that men may by the woorkes of ſuperrogation merit an higher place in heauen for them ſelues and their friends wherof there is no mention in the woord of God: that Church muſt needes erre in matters of do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine. But ſuch a teacher is the Church of Roome, therefore the church of Rome muſt needes erre.</p>
            <p>The maior part of this propoſition hath no war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant in the woord of God.</p>
            <p>The minor is the practiſe of the church of Rome as no deuoted papiſt can deny.</p>
            <p>Therfore all the former concluſions againſt the Church of Rome, that ſhee is not ſubiect to Gods woord in all things: that ſhe teacheth certain points of faith and religion not warranted by the ſcripture, that therefore ſhee is not alwaies led by the ſpirit of God, that ſo of neceſſitie ſhee muſt needes erre, is
<pb facs="tcp:8780:14"/>
manifeſtly prooued, which is more apparant in theſe pointes, that ſhee preſumeth to preferre her decrees, traditions and authoritie aboue the holy Scripture, as no learned papiſt can deny.</p>
            <p>An other obiection our Aduerſaries makes againſt the authority of theſe ſcripture,<label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Obiection. </seg>
               </label> what if a co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>trouerſie do aryſe ſay they about the vnderſtanding of ſome place in Scripture, who muſt then bee iudge thereof but the catholick Church.</p>
            <p>I anſwere not the Church,<label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſwer. </seg>
               </label> but the woord of God ſtill, for if the Scripture be appointed to iudge <note n="(l)" place="margin">Iohn. 12.48.</note> vs all at the laſt day, as our Sauiour Chriſt dooth teſti<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fie, who will deny it to be of force, to iudge all con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trouerſies in Religion, yea euen ſuch as ſpring with in her bowels,<note place="margin">Chriſt and his church, appeale to the ſcripture.</note> for doe wee not all knowe that albeit Satan alledged ſcripture in tempting of Chriſt, yet on<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly by the Scripture the Lord confuted him, <hi>Mat.</hi> 4. <hi>Luk.</hi> 4. And ſo likewiſe did the the true Apoſtles, <note n="(m)" place="margin">1 Cor. 15.3, 4.</note> all falſe Apoſtles.</p>
            <p>We ſe therfore (by Chriſts example and his deare Apoſtles) that the church in all Ages, and in all cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes of cotrouerſie, did ſubmit her iudgment to the holy Scriptu<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e, as the Lord more plainly aunſwered the <hi>Saduces</hi> (pleading a deuorſe betweene man and wife <note n="(n)" place="margin">Deut. 24.1.</note> by <hi>Moſes</hi> permiſsion) and ſaid it was not ſo from the beginning alleadging the firſt inſtitution of mariage not to be diſſolued by any but the maker <note n="(o)" place="margin">Gen. 2.24. &amp; Math. 19.4, 5, 6</note> by more auntient authoritie of the Scripture: wherby they were all put to ſilence.</p>
            <p>But let vs admit the church to haue power to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cyde all controuerſies, yet the ſame muſt euer be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended of that communion of Gods Saintes which ſubmit their iudgment vnto the Scriptures: and not to that malignant ſynagog of ſatan: (I meane the ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed church of Rome) which preſumeth to prefer
<pb facs="tcp:8780:15"/>
her decrees and decretalles to the woord written, which Chriſt hath left as a rule to church, as be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore hath beene prooued.<note place="margin">Mat. 28.20.</note>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">That ignora<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of ſcripture ſho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uld be mother of deuotion, is ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurd.</note>To come to the other pointe which the papiſtes holde that ignorance of ſcripture is mother of deuo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, ſo flat repugnant to this rule of <hi>Dauid,</hi> who wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth <hi>Salomon</hi> to knowe his God, and likewiſe againſt the reproofe of the <hi>Saduces</hi> by our ſauiour Ieſus who charged them all with manifeſt errors, becauſe they knew not the holy Scriptures, <hi>Math. 22.29.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It muſt needes be an abſurde opinion, as to denie an Infant the mothers milke, and yet holde opinion it ſhould growe the better: for ſeeing the woord of God is called the very ſeed of our regeneration, <note n="(p)" place="margin">1 Pet. 1.23. &amp; 2.2.</note> and that pure and ſweeter milke wherby we are no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhed vnto life eternall, how is it poſſible that wee ſhould growe in knowledge, in faith or in repenta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce as the Lord requireth, without the right vnderſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding therof.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Why Popiſh preiſts barre the common reading of the ſcripture.</note>But if you would know the reaſons indeed, why the papiſts barre the common people from reading of the Scriptures: It is becauſe the knowledge therof would bewray and detect all their wil-<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>rſhipings before recyted, to be nothing els but their owne in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uentions, without any warrant from the woord of God,<note place="margin">What is vaine woorſhip.</note> which if all Chriſtians knew to be true, (as be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore hath been prooued) and that our Sauiour reie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cteth the ſame, ſaying to all ſuch that they woorſhip him in vaine, teaching for doctrine mens precepts. <hi>Mat. 15.9.</hi> they would not ſuffer themſelues (like blynde men) to be led ſtill blyndefolde which way they pleaſe: and heeruppon it commeth why they keepe the Scriptures in a ſtraunge language, that ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norant people cannot vnderſtand the ſame, and why their ſeldome popiſh preachers doe in their ſermons
<pb facs="tcp:8780:15"/>
alledge ſo little Scripture, and ſo prophane hiſtories, and why they plant ouer the people ſuch popiſh puſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſles for the moſte part, as can hardly read their latin ſeruice, only to keep them ſtill in ignorance.</p>
            <p>Yet doe the papiſts (to countenance their error) pretend ſome places of the holy Scripture,<note place="margin">An obiection.</note> as that of <hi>Peeter,</hi> where hee ſaith, our brother <hi>Paul</hi> hath writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten ſome things hard to vnderſtand, which they that are vnlearned and vnſtable, peruert. &amp;c. 2. <hi>Pet: 3 16</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Whereuppon they gather that becauſe <hi>Peeter</hi> ſaith ſome places of <hi>Paules</hi> Epiſtles are hard, therfore the whole body of the ſcriptures are harde: or be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe ſome vnlearned men are vnſtable in their waies, therfore all the common people are of that diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition: otherwiſe they would not ſeclude them all from reading the ſcriptures in their mother tounge.</p>
            <p>But to make this more plaine, albeit I might aun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwere <hi>Peeter</hi> with <hi>Peeter,</hi> euen in the verſe before this place alleadged, that <hi>Pauls</hi> Epiſtles and his were both directed to one ſorte of people<note n="(q)" place="margin">2 Pet. 3.15.</note> and therfore ought to bee read of them all, or els to what purpoſe did they write vnto them, yet will I plainly confute their oppinion by other places of the holy Scripture; and that by comparing their doctrine together.</p>
            <p>The Papiſtes teach, that the whole woord of God is hard to vnderſtand.<note place="margin">Compariſons</note>
            </p>
            <p>But this our kinglie Prophet ſaith, That the law of the Lord is eaſie to vnderſtand, and giueth wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome vnto the ſimpleſt.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Pſalmes 19.7.8.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Againe,<note place="margin">Deut. 6.6, 7. Pſalm. 119. Coll. 3.16 Iohn. 5.39.</note> The Papiſtes dehorte ſimple People from reading the Scriptures: contrariewiſe bothe Moyſes, Dauid, Paule, and Chriſte him ſelfe doo warne all men to ſearch the holy ſcriptures that ſo it may dwell plentifullie in them.</p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:8780:16"/>Now let all men iudge that haue the vſe of reaſon, whether it is better to beleeue the papiſts vpon their bare woord in matters of ſaluation,<note place="margin">Whether to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeue papiſts, or Chriſt &amp; his Apoſtles, to be more ſafe.</note> or the counſaile of <hi>Moſes, Dauid, Paul</hi> and <hi>Chriſt</hi> himſelfe being con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trarie therunto: as euerie one may ſee by the former compariſons.</p>
            <p>But to make the abſurditie of the papiſts reaſon, to inhibite lay people the reading of the Scriptures to appeare manifeſt, becauſe ſome places therof bee hard to vnderſtand, as <hi>Peeter</hi> ſayes of <hi>Paules</hi> Epiſtles. It is all one,<note place="margin">Marke theſe compariſons.</note> as if one ſhoulde affirme, that becauſe there be ſome bones in a ſhoulder of mutton, ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it is nothing but bones, and no fleſhe thereon at all: or becauſe ſome places in the riuer be deep, ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore all the riuer from head to foot is deepe, and no ſhallownes to be found therin, which were moſt ridi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culous to affirme: euen ſo is this opinion of the pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſts, that becauſe ſome places in Scripture be hard, therfore all the whole body of the Scripture is hard, ſo as lay people may at no hand read them, expreſly againſt the before alleadged woordes of <hi>Dauid</hi> the Prophet and Chriſt himſelfe, that they are eaſie to vnderſtand, and whoſoeuer lookes for eternall life, he muſt diligently ſearch the holye Scriptures <hi>Pſal, 19.7. Joh. 5.39.</hi> But ſome papiſt may obiect that all this ſore charge laid vpon them,<note place="margin">An obiection</note> to barre ſimple peo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ple the reading of the Scriptures is moſte falſe, for they cauſed one <hi>Gregory Martin</hi> of late to tranſlate the new Teſtament into the engliſh toung, that all ſortes of people might read therof, at their pleaſure and le<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſure.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Aunſwer. </seg>
               </label> I anſwere and graunt indeed, that there is ſuch a booke in the engliſh toung, (though not permitted in England) yet my aſſertion, (<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> they would haue all men ignorant therin) ſtandeth vnto moouable by
<pb facs="tcp:8780:16"/>
diuers reaſons.</p>
            <p n="1">1 Firſt in deferring the tranſlation therof ſo long a time, <hi>videlicet,</hi> almoſt 30 yeares her Maieſties proſperous reigne ouer vs, whereby their good will to ſeeke our ſaluation dooth ſlowly appeare, beſides the omitting of all the olde Teſtament.</p>
            <p n="2">2 Secondly, by the barbarous obſcuritie of the text, which in many places is ſo darck and difficulte, as the common people can hardlye vnderſtand the bare text in engliſh without an Interpreter.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Thirdly, by the infinite number of ſtraunge a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>notations and interpretations, fetched from all ſorts of former wryters how corrupt ſoeuer, for the ſtron<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger maintenance of their groſſe opinions, againſt the plaine text of Scripture in moſte places as before a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leadged.</p>
            <p n="4">4 Fourthly, The councell of Trent forbidding all lay people the reading of the ſciptures, who darre read them that would auoyde his curſe?</p>
            <p>Hauing thus confuted the daungerous errors of both ſortes of aduerſaries againſt this holeſome cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaile of <hi>Dauid</hi> the king, <hi>to knowe and ſerue God.</hi> Let vs now proceede to inquire further, what kinde of God it was, whome <hi>Salomon</hi> was moued ſo earneſtly to ſerue, was it the God of the <hi>Philiſtines,</hi> or the God of the <hi>Amonites Moloch,</hi> 
               <note n="(r)" place="margin">1 Sam. 7.3. Iudg. 2.13. 1 king 11.7.</note> or <hi>Aſtaroth</hi>: No, no, It was the God of his father, <hi>The God of his father,</hi> as if <hi>Dauid</hi> had ſaid vnto him.</p>
            <p>
               <q>O <hi>Salomon</hi> my ſonne, the God of thy father <hi>Dauid</hi> is that onely almightie and eternall God, the crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor, gouernour and preſeruer of heauen and earth and all things therin, who ſo tenderly beloued me thy father, that beeing moſte vnwoorthie and the leaſt <note n="(s)" place="margin">1 Sam. 16.11 12 13</note> and youngeſt of all my bretheren (yet he choſe mee to be the king of <hi>Jrael</hi> to guide and go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerne
<pb facs="tcp:8780:17"/>
his peculier people) euen then when I follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the Ewes with young,<note n="(t)" place="margin">Pſal. 78.71.</note> and as a ſpeciall ſigne ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, before I came to the throne and kingdome, did only deliuer mee from a Lyon and a Beare <note n="(v)" place="margin">1 Sam. 17.4.51.</note> but gaue mee alſo victorie ouer that mightie and mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrous Gyant <hi>Goliath</hi> of <hi>Gath,</hi> that proud boaſting vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>circumſized Philiſtine, who diſdainfully defied the whole hoſt of <hi>Jſrael,</hi> but my God gaue mee ſtrength to cut of his head, therfore know that God, that on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly good God.</q>
            </p>
            <p>Againe, this almightie God of heauen and earth hath doone more for thy father then ſo (for though <hi>Saul</hi> the laſt king my predeceſſor, knew and was en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fourmed by the Prophet <hi>Samuel,</hi> that God had ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed I ſhould ſucceed him, I being then his poor ſonne and ſeruant, yet did the ſeek my vtter diſtructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, (by all meanes poſsible to preue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t Gods purpoſe) but the Lord by his prouidence did ſafelye protecte mee from all manner daungers, (though I was pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſued from place to place) and in his good time bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ught mee to this king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, and now hath ſubdued and ſubiected vnder me, all mine enemies, prolong<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing my reigne to gouern his people full fortie yeeres togither: and hath further graunted my humble re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſt, that thou my ſonne <hi>Salomon</hi> ſhalt ſucceede mee in my kingdome, therfore know thou that God that gratious good God.</p>
            <p>Again, this almightie God of heauen and earth, hath yet done more for thy father <hi>Dauid</hi> then all be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore mentioned, for wheras all mankinde by the fear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full fall of <hi>Adam</hi> and <hi>Eue</hi> our firſt Parents, were iuſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly depriued of all felicitie, and become Satans vaſſals ſubiect to all miſerie.</p>
            <p>If then it ſo pleaſed his gratious goodnes, by his couenant of grace, to indent with mankinde, that the
<pb facs="tcp:8780:17"/>
womans ſeede ſhould<note n="(x)" place="margin">Gen. 3.15.</note> cruſh in peeces the head of the ſerpent: &amp; afterwards, the Lord declared in more ſpeciall manner to our forefathers <hi>Abraham Jſacc</hi> and <hi>Jacob,</hi> that in their ſeede (as ſpeaking of one) <note n="(a)" place="margin">Gen. 12.18.</note> the promiſed ſauiour ſhould proccede: And becauſe the laſt of theſe three Patriarchs had twelue ſonnes, who were all diſperſed into twelue trybes, whereof this great people are ſprung as wee ſee, it further pleaſed his almightie Maieſtie to make it manifeſt vnto all poſterities, out of which trybe the Sauiour ſhoulde ſpring, that is to ſay, from the trybe <note n="(b)" place="margin">Gen. 49.10.</note> of <hi>Juda,</hi> out of which ſtock <note n="(c)" place="margin">1 Cro. 23.4.</note> my father I ſay came: yea the Lord hath reuealed and ſworne to me thy father, that out of the iſſue of mine owne bodie,<note n="(d)" place="margin">Pſal. 89.26, 27 &amp; 132.11.</note> this bleſſed <hi>Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſias</hi> ſhalbe incarnate who ſhall ſaue his people from all their ſinnes. In whome I beleeue, (as in mine on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie Sauiour) <note n="(e)" place="margin">Pſal. 27.1. &amp; 31.5.</note> and ſo doe commend my ſoule into his hands: O my ſonne <hi>Salomon,</hi> knowe thou there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore that God, that euerlaſting good God of thy fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>Dauid.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This holy Exhortation beeing giuen to <hi>Salomon, to knowe and ſerue his God,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Vnder the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of Salomon, the dutie of all degrees is diſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bed.</note> wee are to gather thus much, that vnder his perſon (as principall) the dutie of all degrees is diſcrybed: for <hi>Dauid</hi> ſpeaking to <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lomon</hi> as cheife, in the preſence (as it were of all his Subiects dooth include and inſinuare their duties alſo: that euerie one of them in their place and cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling ought diligentlye and faithfullye to learne and knowe to ſerue this God.</p>
            <p>By this rule may ſome ſay, you woulde haue all degrees to become Scripture men and to carrie the Bible in their handes to Sermons: but that were a ſhame, for men of high eſtate and calling: it is not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeeming their places and callings to ſtudie the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures.</p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:8780:18"/>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Aunſwer. </seg>
               </label> The anſwere heer unto is plain and eaſie, for there is hardly any calling in this world greater then <hi>Salo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon</hi>: hee was heire apparant vnto a mightie king and put in poſſeſsion not his crowne and kingdome, in his fathers lyfe time, and yet his father <hi>Dauid</hi> giues him in charge,<note place="margin">Great men of ne<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ceſsitie muſt ſtudie the ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures.</note> that <hi>Salomon</hi> himſelf ſhould <hi>know and ſerue his God</hi> which can neuer rightly be perfourmed, but firſt of neceſsitie hee muſt learn the holie ſcriptures, which conteine the matter and manner of Gods woorſhip and all other dutie whatſoeuer.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">An other obie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction.</note>But yet by your leaue (ſir) ſuch as be great men of high eſtate or calling, they may well deferre the ſtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die of ſcripture vntill their olde age: and in the mean time follow their pleaſures, and towards their latter and then learn to dye well.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſwer. </seg>
               </label> This vaine excuſe, is plainly refelled by <hi>Salomons</hi> example, who beeing a young prince and but new<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly entred into his kingdome,<note place="margin">Young princes and noblemen muſt ſtudie the ſcriptures.</note> was euen exhorted by <hi>Dauid</hi> his father to learne to knowne the Scriptures, as in an other place hee perſwadeth all young per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons by way of a queſtion ſaying, where withall ſhall a young-man redreſſe his wayes, but <note n="(f)" place="margin">Pſal. 119.9.</note> by guy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding the ſame according to Gods woord: the conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuall holy meditation whereof, is a ſure ſigne of a bleſſed man <note n="(g)" place="margin">Pſalm. 11.2 and 119. wholy</note> as himſelfe dooth witneſſe.</p>
            <p>And <hi>Salomon</hi> likewiſe following his good father dooth aduiſe all eſtates and callings not to forget to ſerue their God during their young yeares, before olde age dooth ſteale vppon them.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Ecleſiaſtes. 12.1.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thus doe you ſee all excuſes remooued to hinder great men from ſtudying the ſcriptures euen during their young:<note place="margin">To protract the ſtudie of the ſcriptures moſt dangerous.</note> and youthfull yeares, whom to deferre vntill their olde age is moſte daungerous: for it is but as a dreame for them to dye well, if they haue no
<pb facs="tcp:8780:18"/>
care in the meane ſpace liue wel: or can they at all liue well indeed, and knowe not Gods law the rule of well dooing, or hath any eſtate a leaſe of his life to liue vntil olde age? or any good aſſurance before<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hand, that then they ſhall haue grace to knowe and ſerue God, hauing all their former yeares reiected the meanes to attaine thereunto in neglecting the ſtudie of the holy Scripture or diligently to frequent holy exerciſes, oh how ſore be ſuch men deluded.<note place="margin">An obiection.</note>
            </p>
            <p>But it may be obiected by ſuch a great perſonage if I ſhould be knowen vnto my ſuperiours, to beco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>e a ſtudient in the holy ſcriptures,<label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſwere </seg>
               </label> or to carie the book of God in my handes, I ſhould to much diſcredit my calling.</p>
            <p>Let all great perſons conſider better of that which followeth: Shall it bring no diſhonor vnto their pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, to be ſeene with prophane bookes of pleaſure in their hands, as bookes of loue, poetrie and ſuch like: and ſhall it procure diſgrace to thier perſons to hold the holy Bible in their hands?<note place="margin">None but care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe perſons of their ſaluation will carp at ſuch as ſtudie the ſcripture.</note> How great an abſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditie is this, to immagine that the book of Chriſt Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus (in whome only they looke for ſaluation) ſhould procure their diſgrace amongſt their fellow chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans: as though it were vnbeſeeming great men too knowe the miſerie of their redemption, or how they ſhould ſerue their bleſſed Redemer, which no calling will carpe at, but ſuch graceleſſe perſons as haue no care nor conſcience at all of their owne ſaluation.</p>
            <p>And truely if great men were well acquainted with ſuch excellent matters and variable chaunge thereof,<note place="margin">The Holy ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turee before all other writings for excellent matter, and vari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie therof.</note> as is plentifully expreſſed in the holye ſcriptures, of what point ſoeuer they woulde bee reſolued, either touching this world or the world to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>e: they would preferre the ſtudie therof to all other pleaſures and ſo dayly ſeuer and ſequeſter them ſelues for one hower
<pb facs="tcp:8780:19"/>
at the leaſt, at morne, noone or night, to meditate &amp; contemplate the holy woord of God.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">1 Of the vſe and end of all things created.</note>For firſt, if they would know the courſe &amp; creatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of all things created within the compaſſe of mans capa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>citie, with the right vſe and end of euerie thing, the firſt booke of <hi>Moſes</hi> called <hi>Geneſis,</hi> with that of <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lomon</hi> called <hi>Eccle</hi>: will ſatisfie them fully therin.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">2 Of the moſt an<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cient law &amp; ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of gouerme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t.</note>If they would be acquainted with auntient lawes and ſtatutes, how and by what ordinances the moſt auntient fore-fathers were guyded and gouerned, either touching Religion or conuerſation: The firſt fiue books of <hi>Moſes</hi> ſet down in the bible doe plenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully intreat of all ſuch ſpeciall matter as cannot but delight the Reader very much.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">3 Of ancient hiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tories, how gods ſeruauntes haue bene moſt ſtran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gely protected.</note>If they take pleaſure in reading fine hiſtories, how the Seruants of God from time to time haue been moſt ſtraungely protected and preſerued, and that in greateſt and imminent daungers, by the almightie power and prouidence of God: the whole bodie of the Scripture is full of ſuch examples: name<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly the books of <hi>Heſter, Nehimiath, Eſra, Ruth</hi> &amp; ſuch like.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">4 How God in olde time, did o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerthrowe his e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemies.</note>If they would vnderſtand the courſe and ſucceſſe of all the Lords battels in former ages before Chriſt his birth, how ouer hee defended their cauſe and quarrell that put their truſt in him, and on the other ſide diſcomfited, their enemies when they thought them ſelues moſt ſure to preuaile: let them ouer read the bookes of <hi>Exodus, Joſhua, Judges Samuel</hi> both the <hi>Kings</hi> and <hi>Cronicles,</hi> and they will confeſſe they neuer heard the like.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">5 Why in all a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges, Countries &amp; Kingdomes haue bene ſubuerted.</note>If they deſire to ſee and view why Cuntries and kingdomes were ſubuerted in olde time and knowe the ſecrets of many hid miſteries heertofore reueled<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> let the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> peruſe the bookes of all the ptophets with the
<pb facs="tcp:8780:19"/>
reuelation of <hi>S John,</hi> and they will ſatisfie their minds in thoſe points, and further of the comming &amp; reign of Antechriſte the arch-enemie of Chriſte and all faithfull Chriſtians.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">6 The difference between heuenly and earthly wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome.</note>If their mindes bee eleuate to contemplate hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenly thinges, or to ſee into the ſecrets of Nature and grace, what difference there is betweene that wiſdo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>e which comes from aboue, and that which riſeth from humain reaſon and where in all diſtreſſes to ſeek and finde comfort, let them with all diligence reade and conſider the bookes of <hi>Job,</hi> the <hi>Pſalmes,</hi> the Prouerbs of <hi>Salomon</hi> and <hi>Paul</hi> to the <hi>Romanes,</hi> which will con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent them fully in thoſe points.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">7 Of the incom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parable Hiſtorye of our ſauiour Chriſt his birth, doctrine, life and miracles.</note>If they take pleaſure in the hiſtorie of <hi>Chriſt</hi> to ſearch and finde out the whole courſe of his lyfe, do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine and miracles, as of the manner of his concepti<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>on, birth and bringing vp, with the manifolde trour<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>bles, tortures and torments which hee indured for our ſaluation, and to become a perfect paterne of pa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tience and obedience to all poſterities, let them with all reuerence muſe and meditate vppon the foure <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uangeliſtes,</hi> which do moſt plentifully intreat therof.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">8 Of the vertue of Chriſts death, reſurrection and aſſention.</note>Laſtely, if they would gladly knowe the vertue and power of the Lord Ieſus his death, reſurection and aſſention, how hee conquered ſatan, death, hell and damnation, ſatisfied Gods iuſtice, pacified his wrath, and reconciled vs into his loſt fauour to bee made inheritours of his eternall kingdome, and how wee are made pertakers of the ſame: what diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence there is betweene the law and grace, faith and good woorkes, merits and mercie, this mortall lyfe and that bleſſed life to come, and what good men haue ſuffered for Gods cauſes: let them reuoule with all care and conſcience, the acts of the Apoſtles and all the epiſtles of <hi>Paul, Peeter, James</hi> &amp; <hi>John</hi> with the reſt,
<pb facs="tcp:8780:20"/>
and they ſhall gaine ſuch encreaſe of knowledge in heauenly miſteries as they would not forgoe, for all the pleaſures and treaſures in this life.</p>
            <p>But if ſome great men (for all that hath been ſaid) will not bee aduiſed to ſtudie the Scriptures, let all ſuch knowe from the mouth of Chriſte Ieſus (how great ſoeuer they bee) that who ſoeuer is aſhamed to profeſſe him and his comfortable Goſpell in this wretched world <note n="(g)" place="margin">Mar. 8.38. Luke. 9.26.</note> of thoſe perſons will the Lord Ieſus be then aſhamed, when they ſhall appeare be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore his heauenly father in his celeſtiall kingdome: which wil bring more grief to their ſoules at that day then they haue had pleaſure in their life before.</p>
            <p>Hauing laboured all this while as it were, to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pare the way to the ſeruice of God, let vs now come to the ſubſtance therof,<note place="margin">what the ſeruice of God is, and of whome to be perfourmed.</note> what it is rightly to worſhip and ſerue God, and how it muſt bee perfourmed of all both generally as wee be Chriſtians and perticu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lerly in our places and callings.</p>
            <p>To returne therefore vnto our Text, <hi>Dauid</hi> the king exhorteth all men to know and ſerue God, but the way how it muſt be perfourmed, hee diſcribeth more plainly in other places, namely in the 119 <hi>Pſal. videlicet</hi> according to the Lords owne commaunde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments declared in his law,<note place="margin">How to know and serue God.</note> which <hi>Salomon</hi> tearmeth the ſumme of mans dutie <hi>Eccle. 12.13.</hi> O then let vs ſtriue by all meanes poſsible: firſt to learn and know theſe holy commaundements with the true ſcience and meaning of euerie one, and afterwardes to put them in daylie practiſe, as wee deſire to pleaſe the Lord God.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">The ſum of the two tables o the law.</note>The ten Commaundements of the Almightie, which hee gaue to <hi>Moſes</hi> in Tables of ſtone, is com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly called the law of the Lord, becauſe they com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehend that moſte holy and perfect rule of rightu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſnes,
<pb facs="tcp:8780:20"/>
which himſelf preſcrided for vs to obſerue, bothe in that dutie due to his Maieſtie, conteined in the foure firſt Commaundements, and in our ordina<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rie dealing and proceeding one with an other, as we are all bretheren in Chriſt, and fellowe members of his miſticall bodie, which is briefly expreſſed in the laſt ſix Commaundements.</p>
            <p>To runne therefore ſpeedilie ouer all the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maundements of bothe Tables,<note place="margin">The firſt Table conteineth that ſeruice due to God himſelf<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </note> (for I doe not ſtand fullye dilate fully of them) in the former table which ſpecially concerneth that ſeruice or woorſhippe due vnto God: wee haue to obſerue foure ſpeciall points according to the foure formoſt Commaundements. 1 The firſt dooth expreſſe what God only is to bee worſhiped, and the reaſon to mooue vs thervnto.</p>
            <p n="2">2 The ſecond, with what kinde of woorſhippe he will be pleaſed.</p>
            <p n="3">3 The thirde, how and after what maner it muſt be doone.</p>
            <p n="4">4 The fourth, of the time and day when the Lord will haue his woorſhip &amp; ſeruice vſually performed.</p>
            <p>Now let vs a little conſider in perticulers, of eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie one of theſe holy Comaundements: In the firſt, it is ſaid, God ſpake theſe woords and ſaid, I am thy Lord thy God which brought thee of <hi>Egipt &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">1 Commaund.</note>
               <hi>Thou ſhalt haue no other Gods but mee &amp;c.</hi> In theſe few woords, hee plainlye expreſſeth whom hee will haue woorſhiped, that is him ſelfe alone,<note place="margin">Why God only is to be worſhi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped.</note> (ſecluding all other in heauen and in earth) and the reaſon is ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded becauſe hee onlye brought vs out of bondage, which by <hi>Egipt</hi> is ment, from ſprituall thrall dome of Satan and ſinne by the only meanes of Ieſus Chriſt.</p>
            <p>The ſecond Commaundemet. <hi>Thou ſhalt not make to thy ſelf any grauen Image &amp;c.</hi> In this Commaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dement, God dooth not only forbid all manner falſe
<pb facs="tcp:8780:21"/>
woorſhip contrarie to his wil,<note place="margin">2 Commaunde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, that God onelye is to bee worſhiped after his woord.</note> but threatneth a heuy iudgement to ſuch, whome hee tearmeth haters of his Maieſtie, but hee further diſcribeth the ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance of that woorſhip which hee repuireth, that is to ſay to keep his Commaundements: calling thoſe perſons ſuch onlye as looue him, with promiſe to ſhew great mercies vnto them.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">3 Commaund: That wee muſt woorſhip God, with entire affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction.</note>The third Commaundement, <hi>Thou ſhalt not take the name of the Lord thy God in vain. &amp;c.</hi> In this Com<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>maundement the manner of Gods woorſhip is de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribed, that is to ſay, not vainly, coldely, diſſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>blingly or prophanely: but truely, zealouſly, ſimply, and ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerely, according to his owne preſcribed ordinances, which is heere included, though not expreſſed: for as the commaunding of any vertue excludeth euer the contrarie vice, ſo the forbiding of any vice doth euer require the contrarie vertue, as in this place.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">4 Commaund: Of the ſet time when God will be worſhiped.</note>The fourth Commaundement, <hi>Remember thou keepe holy the Sabaoth day,</hi> in this Commaundement, the Lord appointeth one day in euerie weeke, to be wholy dedicate vnto his ſeruice, In which wee muſt ceaſe from our vſuall labours: the vſe wherof is ſtill obſerued, though the day was altered vpon iuſt oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion, and chaunged from Saturday vntill Sunday, which is more truely called the Lords day by the firſt Chriſtians,<note n="(h)" place="margin">Math. 28.1. 1 Cor. 16.2. Reuel. 1.10.</note> becauſe as that day Chriſte roſe from his graue: But becauſe this holy-daye is ſo much prophayned of all ſortes of people: which of all other Commaundements is moſte neceſſarielye enioyned to bee kept holy: by this woord <hi>Remember</hi> and the Lords owne Example, not that it is greater then any of the former, but beeing rightlye ſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctified of all, it dooth make vs more fit to keepe all the reſt, and ſo becommeth a ſure ſigne and ſeale of ſanctification <note n="(i)" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d. 31.13, 14.</note> betweene God and vs, therefore I
<pb facs="tcp:8780:21"/>
will more plainely deſcribe the very right vſe of all the Lords Sabaoths.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Jſay</hi> in the 58, Chapter of his propheſie, deſcribeth briefly the right obſeruation therof in theſe woords, ſpeaking as it were in the perſon of God: If thou turne away thy foote vppon my Sabaothes <note n="(k)" place="margin">Iſay. 58.13, 14.</note> from dooing thine owne will one mine holy day, and call the Sabaoth a delight to conſecrate it as glorious to the Lord, and ſhalt honor him,<note place="margin">The right vſe of euery ſaboth.</note> not dooing his owne waies, not ſeeking thine owne will, not ſpeaking a vaine woord, then ſhalt thou delight in the Lord &amp;c.</p>
            <p>By theſe few woordes wee may plainly perceiue two neceſſarie points to be obſerued in the right vſe of euerie Sabaoth. The former,<note place="margin">Two neceſſary pointes, in obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing everye ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>both.</note> that wee lay aſide as that day all our owne wills, woords and woorkes, as the Lord commaundeth: The latter, that we vſually frequent the Lords Sanctuaries and there reuerently woorſhippe and ſerue him as he enioyneth vs. That is to ſay, to call vppon his name, to heare his woord preached, to perticipate his ſacraments, to ſing the Lords prayſes, and to perfourme ſuch other chriſtian duties as ſhalbe publiquely enioined of all: and in the meane ſpace, to muſe &amp; meditate of that which hath been heard, to talke and conferre of it one with an other, to viſit the ſick, to comfort the comfortles, to releiue the oppreſſed, and ſuch like: But our olde enemie ſatan (who enuyeth our welfare abooue all meaſure) knowing the Lords day to be our market day for the food of our ſoules,<note place="margin">How ſatan la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boureth to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phane the ſaboth &amp; to hinder our ſaluation, all he can.</note> dooth labour to hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der it all that hee can, partly by planting inſufficient and vngodly paſtors &amp; preachers ouer Gods people, ſuch as either lack ſkil or goodwil to doe their duties in due reaſon, and partlye by making the woord vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>profitable in the hearts of the hearers, (thouhh wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dering
<pb facs="tcp:8780:22"/>
by thoughts) or keeping the people other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe occupied, that they ſhould not heare the woord at all, and ſo dooth lull bothe ſortes in the cradle of ſecuritie to their endleſſe diſtruction, except they repent and forſake ſuch waies in time.</p>
            <p>In regarde wherof, how expedient it is, for all ſuch as looue God and long for ſaluation to obſerue the counſaile which <hi>Salomon</hi> giueth, videlicet, when they enter into the Lords houſe<note n="(l)" place="margin">Eccles. 4.7.</note> to look vnto their feet &amp;c. wherby our affections are vnderſtood, ſo that aſwel the Miniſter is fore warned to become (as <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith) <note n="(m)" place="margin">1 Cor. 4 12. How to cary our ſelues in Gods houſe.</note> a faithfull diſpence of the Lords ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crets, as the people to harke and marke what is ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken, to refourme their Religion and liues thereafter that ſo their indeuours may not be in vaine but the Lord our redeemer glorified in bothe.</p>
            <p>For their better prepararion to ſanctifie each Lords day, it ſhall be good therefore for euerie one priuately before publique prayer time,<note place="margin">How to prepare our ſelues to Gods woorſhip.</note> to call vpon God in their owne ſeceret chabers for grace &amp; dire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, to examin their owne hearts in what caſe they ſtand, that wherin ſoeuer they finde their own wa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts, the may vſe all holy means to be furthered &amp; ſtre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned in the true feare and ſeruice of the Lord, which if euerie Chriſtian would duely obſerue, before they went to heare the woorde of God preached, then ſhould they be ſure to profit thereby<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> for there was neuer anye that euer ſoughte the Lord with their whole heart, &amp; begged grace of his goodnes to that end, whome wee read to haue been ſent away emp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie.</p>
            <p>To come now to the ſecond Table, which con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cernes our dutie one to an other, as fellow members of that miſticall bodie wherof Chriſt Ieſus is the hed there be ſix co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maundements belonging therunto.</p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:8780:22"/>
               <note place="margin">5 Commaund.</note>The firſt whereof, which is the fift in number, dooth knit vs altogither in one corporation, the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrate to rule, and the people to obey, as the Lord requireth.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">6 Commaund.</note>The ſixt, dooth teach vs how wee ought to liue peaceably, and to preſerue one an others life.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">7 Commaund.</note>The ſeuenth, how to keep the mariage bed vnde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>filed.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">8 Commaund.</note>The eight, that in no wiſe we defraude our neigh<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>bour of his goods.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">9 commaund.</note>The ninth, that wee impare not our neighbours good name.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">10 Commaund.</note>The tenth and laſt, that euerie perſone (of what degree ſoeuer) content him ſelfe with his eſtate.</p>
            <p>But to ſpeak ſomething more of theſe latter Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maundements (as of the former) the firſt, which is the fift in number, <hi>Honor thy Father and thy mother,</hi>
               <note place="margin">The true ſence of the fift Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maundement.</note> 
               <hi>that thy dayes may bee long &amp;c.</hi> In this Commaunde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment albeit the dutie of all inferiours to their ſupe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riours, bee ſpeciallye ment in this woord honor, yet the like dutie of all ſuperiors vnto their inferiours, is likewiſe conteined vnder theſe woordes of father and mother, that is to ſay, of Magiſtrates to gouern, of Miniſters to preach, of Parents to teach, and of maſters to inſtruct their charge and familye in the feare of God: Then ſhall bothe the Church and com<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mon welth floriſh and euery one proſper in his place and calling, as the Lord promiſeth in his commaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dement.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">The true mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of the 6. Commaund.</note>The ſixt Commaundement, <hi>Thou ſhalt doe no mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der.</hi> In this Commaundement is forbidden all man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner violence il-wil or purpoſe to hurt our neighbor, and requireth vnitie and amitie, to abound in all per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons.</p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:8780:23"/>The ſeuenth, <hi>Thou ſhalt not commit adulterie,</hi> this commaundement inhibiteth not onlye the acte of a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dulterie it ſelf but alſo all inordinate luſts tending to that end, (eſpecially in maried perſons) and chargeth each one to keep his owne bodie chaſt for the Lord. or to vſe that lawfull meanes of mariage, which him ſelfe hath ordeined for auoyding of ſinne.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">The true mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ninge of the 8. Commaun.</note>The eight, <hi>Thou ſhalt not ſteale,</hi> this commaunde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, abandoneth all vniuſt, falſe and fraudulent de<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ling, from amongſt all men, and requireth all iuſte and vpright proceeding amongſt all degrees and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons to the common benefit one of another.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">The true mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of the 9. Commaund.</note>The ninth, <hi>Thou ſhalt not beare falſe witnes againſt thy Teighbour</hi>: this commaundement, not onlye ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cludeth all falſe othes, and detracting one another, but enioyneth on the contrarie a tender regarde to maintain and defend each one an others good name.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">The true mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of the 10. Com.</note>The tenth, <hi>Thou ſhalt not couet thy neighbours houſe.</hi> this commaundement forbideth all couetous deſire to haue any thing that belongs to our neighbour, (albeit wee meane to pay truely for it) except the partie be willing to part with it, which plainlye diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cribeth before our eyes, the perfect patterne of a true Chriſtian, <hi>videlicet,</hi> ſo contentedly to liue in his eſtate and calling (how meane ſo euer) that hee hath no deſire to haue the ſame better din reſpect of outward things, but euer to referre his will to the Lords.</p>
            <p>Hauing thus briefly diſcourſed ouer the generall dutie of all manner chriſtians ſo farre as the lawe re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quireth at their hands, which euerie one ought to put in practiſe according to the counſaile of our king<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly prophet, <hi>know and ſerue God,</hi> it followeth now by the ſame rule alſo to deſcribe the dutie of all manner perſons, in their perticuler places and callings, and to exhort euerie one thereunto.</p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:8780:23"/>
               <note place="margin">The Prince his dutie.</note>Art thou a Prince or Potentate in this world, as mightie in power as <hi>Dauid</hi> or <hi>Salomon</hi> knowe what thy God requireth of thee in thy place and calling, that thou profeſſe and preferre true Religion, as the ſame is preſcribed in the woorde of God, and to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure ſo much as in thee lyeth, that all thy people af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>may learne the ſame, and ſpecially <hi>to ſerue God</hi> there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, that he may bleſſe thee in all thy waies.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">The magiſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rates duty.</note>Art thou a Magiſtrate in high auctoritie vnder the Prince? know what thy God requireth of thee: that thou beate downe all ſinne &amp; wilful ſinners <note n="(n)" place="margin">Rom. 13.1.6.</note> and that thou giue countenance to good men and godlines, looke therfore thou ſerue God therafter.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">The noble man duty.</note>Art thou a noble man of great eſtate or calling, knowe what thy God requireth of thee, that thou go before others in godlines &amp; that vertue, thou liue within the compaſſe of thy calling, that thou be mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derate in dyet, pleaſures and apparrell, that thou be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come a good benefactor to the Church and co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth, looke therfore thou ſerue God heerafter.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">The Iudge his duty.</note>Art thou a Iudge in cauſes and controuerſies, to giue equall doome between partie and partie, know what thy God requireth of thee, that thou heare in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>differently all mens cauſes. that thine heart &amp; hands be free from all brybes, that thou be cleane from par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiall affections, of looue or hatred, that the feare of God be euer before thine eyes, that thou haue no re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect of perſons, that thy iudgement ſtand with iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice and equitie, looke therfore thou ſerue God in this ſorte, that he may maintaine thee to doe him much ſeruice.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">The Iuſtice of p<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ace duty.</note>Art thou a Iuſtice of peace or quorum, knowe what thy God requireth of thee, that thou puniſh all peace breakers and vagrant perſons with all others that liue diſorderlie, looke therfore thou doe ſo in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed,
<pb facs="tcp:8780:24"/>
and ſeeke to ſerue God dayly more and more.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">The man in cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dit his dutie.</note>Art thou in credit or countenance any way, know what thy God requireth of thee, that thou liue ſober<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly without vainglory, that thou euer pittie all poore ſutors, that thou fauour and further their good diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>patch, looke therfore thou ſerue God accordingly.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">The Maior and Sheriffs dutie.</note>Art thou a maior, Sheriffe, Alderman, or other hed officer in Citie or Cuntrie, know what thy God requireth of thee, that thou haue ſpeciall care and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>garde to the common benefite of that corporation where thou art planted, that thou baniſh roges and all ſuch perſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s as liue in idlenes, gaming or ſuch like, that thou comfort and cheriſh all ſuch good mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers, as beeing but poore ſeeke to liue iuſtlye vppon their owne trauell in ſome lawful calling, looke ther<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fore thou ſerue God therafter,</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">The Miniſters dutie.</note>Art thou a Miniſter and haſte a charge of ſoules, knowe what thy God requireth of thee, that thou haue no moe Church-charges then thou canſt well diſcharge, that thou be apt <note n="(o)" place="margin">1 Timo. 3.2. 2. Timo. 4.2.</note> able and wel-willing to preach and teach Gods woord vnto them, that thou <note n="(p)" place="margin">1 Peet. 5.2.3.</note> perfourme the ſame duely and truely, that thy life be anſwerable <note n="(q)" place="margin">Mat. 5.16.</note> vnto thy doctrine, looke therfore thou ſerue God in this ſorte, for feare of the <note n="(r)" place="margin">1 Cor. 9.16. The Land-Lord h<gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s dutie.</note> woe if thou faint or fall therin.</p>
            <p>Art thou a land-Lord and haſt Tenants vnder thee, know what thy God requireth of thee, that thou re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member both thou and they are bought bothe with one price, and that with God there is no reſpect of perſons, that hee deteſteteth all violence and oppre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſſion. and appointeth each one to liue in his calling, looke therfore thou giue them no cauſe to complane leaſt thou and thine doe ſmart for the ſame: ſeeke therfore to ſerue God after theſe rules.</p>
            <p>A<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> thou a rich man that hath this worlds good,
<pb facs="tcp:8780:24"/>
knowe what thy God requireth of thee, that thou re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member to bee <note n="(s)" place="margin">1 Tim. 6.17, 18</note> rich in good woorkes, to releiue the poore, the fatherleſſe and widowes, to help poos ſchollers, priſoners ct ſuch like, looke therfore thou ſerue God in this ſorte, ſo ſhall thy treaſure increaſe in heaun.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">The Lawyers dutie.</note>Art thou a lawyer and pleadeſt mens cauſes, know what thy God requireth of thee, that thou doe not bolſter vp naughtie matters, neither yet pleade wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully againſt co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſcience: that thou faint not at any time to pleade right and iuſtice, aſ well for the poore that hath no fees to pay, as for the rich who filleth the purſſe, that thou deale faithfully in all mens cauſes, &amp; tell them truely the ſtate of their caſe at firſt, as at the laſt ſo uere as thou canſt, O looke thou ſerue God af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter this manner, ſo ſhalt thou haue fauour with him and all good men.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">The Marchant his dutie.</note>Art thou a Merchant, a Mercer or ſuch like, know what thy God requireth of thee, that thou deal with ſound and ſubſtantiall wares, and part with the ſame at a reaſonable price: that thou buy and ſell without othes or lying, &amp; in all thy dealings vſe true waights and meaſures: O then be careful to ſerue God in this ſorte, that hee may proſper thy lawfull indeuours.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">The Father &amp; maſters dutie.</note>Art thou a Maſter, a father or houſholder, knowe what thy God, requireth of thee, that thou traine vp thy ſeruants, children and pre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tiſes in the true know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge and feare God: looke then thou ſerue God and become carefull.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">The married mans dutie.</note>Art thou a marryed man of what calling ſoeuer, knowe what thy God requireth of thee: that thou learne of Chriſt the head of his Church <note n="(t)" place="margin">Ephſ. 5.25, 26, 33.</note> to noriſh and cheriſh, to guyde and gouerne thy wife in his feare, and euer beare with her as the weaker veſſell, looke therefore thou ſerne God after this manner.</p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:8780:25"/>
               <note place="margin">The wiues dutie</note>Art thou a wife of what degree ſoeuer, knowe what thy God requireth of thee, that thou learne of the Church, as the Church dooth to Chriſte, <note n="(v)" place="margin">Epheſ, 5.22, 23.34.</note> to ſubmit thy ſelf to thy husband in all thinges, to bee guyded as hee will in all lawfull thinges, that thou loue and obey him as thy head and husband, looke therfore thou ſerue God as hee commaundeth thee.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">The Artificers dutie.</note>Art thou a tradeſ-man, artificer or ſuch like, know what thy God requireth of thee, that thou make good ſtuffe without fraude or couin: that it, tend more to proffite then pride, and that thou doe not ouerprize it in ſelling, to abuſe the ſimplicitie of the buyer, looke therfore to ſerue God faithfully.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">The ſchoolema<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters dutie.</note>Art thou a Schole-maſter, and haſt charge of youth, know what thy God requireth of thee, not to traine them vp with prophane fables, but in ſuch knowe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge as tendes to godlynes, looke then thou ſerue God thereafter.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">The poormans dutie,</note>Art thou a poore man or day-taile laborer, knowe what thy God requireth of thee, that thou bee well content with thy calling, that thou labour faithfulie, in thy woork, and vſe not to loyter in thy maſters ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence, looke therfore thou ſerue God as he enioineth thee.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">The ſeruants dutie.</note>Art thou a ſeruant, an aprentice or ſuch like, know what thy God requireth of thee, that thou purlome not thy maſters goods or wares, nor deale vniuſtlie in thine accompts, that thou ſeeke not to pleaſe him only in preſence but <note n="(v)" place="margin">The vnmaried per<gap reason="illegible: missing" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ons dutie 1 Cor. 6 15.16.20.</note> aſ well in abſence ſerue him faithfully, look therfore thou ſerue God in this ſorte.</p>
            <p>Art thou a ſingle man or woman, know what thy God requireth of thee, that thou keep thy bodye as his holy temple <note n="(x)" place="margin">Epheſ. 6.5.7.8.</note> that thou abſtaine from all forni<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cation, and auoide all tempting occaſſions therunto, or els vſe the lawful means of mariage <note n="(y)" place="margin">Hebr. 13.4.</note> as a reme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die
<pb facs="tcp:8780:25"/>
againſt ſinne and all ſinfull motions, looke ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore in any caſe thou ſeeke and ſerue God after his rule, that hee may bleſſe thy lawfull deſires.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">The vſurers du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie.</note>Art thou an vſurer or wicked oppreſſor, knowe what thy God requireth of thee, to make reſtitution and forſake all thy ſinners, to become a new man out of hand <note n="(z)" place="margin">Amos. 6.3. Eccle. 5.7.</note> and not to deferre the ſame any longer, leaſt the Lords wrath fall ſuddainly vppon thee, oh then looke thou ſerue God diligently heerafter.</p>
            <p>Hauing thus briefly poſted ouer the ſeuerall dutie of euerie perſon, in his perticuler place and calling, let vs now come to ſpeake of that other point touch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the manner of Gods woorſhippe, with what a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ffections hee is to be ſerued:<note place="margin">The ſecond part with what affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions God is to be woorſhiped</note> which beeing duely and deeply conſidered, will bring no ſmall inſtruction &amp; comfort, for the Lord being of a ſpirituall ſubſtance, eternall, infinite, almightie and mercifull, a hater of ſinne, and louer of goodnes, moſte wiſe, moſte iuſt, moſt holy and righteous, out of whoſe fulnes we all receiue that meaſure of grace which wee haue to doe good: hee cannot away to be otherwiſe ſerued, then beſt agreeth with his owne nature, that is to bee woorſhiped <note n="(a)" place="margin">Iohn 4.24.</note> in ſpirit and trueth, and as <hi>Dauid</hi> ſaith heare with a perfect heart and a willing minde: not with a peeuiſh, peruerſe or partial heart, or with a wicked, wilful and wayward minde, but with a per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect heart and a willing minde: as that fourme and manner of faithful ſeruice where withall hee is only delighted.</p>
            <p>The heart of man,<note place="margin">Two fit ſimiles.</note> is fitly compared to the root of a tree, which beeing ſound dooth nouriſh the bran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches, and bring foorth ſound frute: It is alſo likened to the head of a fountain, which beeing ſweet, doth ſend Soorth wholſom and ſweet water, but either of them beeing corrupted, doe bring foorth the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trarie:
<pb facs="tcp:8780:26"/>
Euen ſuch is the heart <note n="(b)" place="margin">Gen. 6.5.</note> and minde of man; by nature, (as wee all lye corrupted in <hi>Adam</hi>) till we be renued and regenerate by grace, and therfore as Chriſt ſaith, can bring forth no goodnes <note n="(c)" place="margin">Mat. 7.18.</note> naturally, for out of the heart proceedeth euill thoughts, adul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teries, fornications, murthers, thefts, <note n="(d)" place="margin">Mark. 7.21, 22.</note> couetouſnes, wickednes, deceit, vncleannes, a wicked eye, back<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byting, pride and fooliſhnes.</p>
            <p>But the heart and minde of man, being purged and purified by faith <note n="(e)" place="margin">Acts. 15.9.</note> in Chriſt, muſt of force then bring foorth contrarie frute, as looue, ioy, peace, long ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ffering, gentlenes, goodnes, faith, meeknes, tempe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance as <hi>S Paul</hi> witneſſeth <hi>Gal, 5.22.23.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Out of that which hath been ſaid, I conclude thus much that the heart of man,<note place="margin">The ſeuerall properties of the hart &amp; minde.</note> is as it were the very root and fountaine to carrie and conuey all his affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions to good or euill which way it luſteth, and the minde being likewiſe the life of the ſoule, to giue life and ſtrength to the ſencible parts, powers and facul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties of ſoule and bodie, to proſecute that which the heart moſte affects:<note place="margin">Keepe thy hart dilligently.</note> which beeing duely obſerued of all the counſail that <hi>Salomon</hi> preſcribeth in the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerbs, is very profitable and moſte needfull, to keep our hearts with all diligence, becauſe out of them ſpringeth life. <hi>Pro.</hi> 4.23, &amp; to ſerue the Lord with our whole heart, minde, ſoule and ſtrength<note n="(f)" place="margin">Duet. 6.5. &amp;</note> as we are enioyned in many other places of the holy Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 119.</note>And wheras <hi>Dauid</hi> teacheth that we muſt ſerue God with a perfect heart, &amp; a willing minde, which ſecludeth a double &amp; diſſembling heart, with a foo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh feyned &amp; froward minde,<note place="margin">The papiſts &amp; carnal goſpellers reproued again.</note> heerby again the tem<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>poriſing papiſts and carnall goſpellers are both very plainly and roundly reprooued: for would any of the papiſts come to our Church (but the woord preched
<pb facs="tcp:8780:26"/>
would root out their errors) were not the danger of law to compell them, or that they cory fauour with ſuperiour Magiſtrates in hope of credit,<note place="margin">Temporizing papiſts cannot ſerue God.</note> preferment or ſuch like, &amp; ſo long, their conſciences muſt needs giue euidence againſt them, that they cannot pleaſe God, for they doe not ſerue him with a perfect heart and a willing minde.</p>
            <p>Againe, all ſuch goſpellers, as make a faire ſhew in comming to the Church, and yet while the woord is read and preached, are tatling and talking, wagging and walking or haue their mindes otherwiſe occupi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, ſome about their farmes,<note place="margin">Carnall Goſpel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers cannot pleaſe God.</note> ſome about their oxen and ſome about their pleaſures or ſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>e like prophanes doe theſe men ſerue God with a perfect heart and a willing minde: there conciences cry out to the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trarie and ſo long ſure they cannot pleaſe God.</p>
            <p>Oh then in any caſe let vs take heed, that wee doe not become mockers of God, to woorſhip him with our bodies, when our ſoules are farre from him,<note place="margin">Who mocke God</note> we honour him with our tounges, when our hearts wa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der from him: to ſerue him in part, ſome peece of the Sabaoth, and to ſerue ſinne and ſatan the reſt: for God will not be mocked, hee is euer iealous of his owne glorie,<note n="(q)" place="margin">Gal. 6.7.</note> who will either haue the whole day or no part thereof, hee will haue the whole bodie and ſoule or no part of them: he wil be woorſhiped with a perfect heart and a willing mind, or els not at all.</p>
            <p>For if any of vs all had a ſeruant that were an idle fellow, forſlowed his buſines,<note place="margin">How wee would vſe a bad ſeruant</note> mynded other mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, or went to his woorke like a bear to the ſtake, full ſore againſt his wil: would wee be pleaſed with his ſeruice, and not rather ſet him packing out of our dores.</p>
            <p>Oh then let vs learne to become wiſe-harted, to iudge our ſelues in time, that except wee all amend,
<pb facs="tcp:8780:27"/>
our wants, and caſt away our coldenes a careleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes in Gods ſeruice,<note place="margin">Let vs iudge our ſelues in time.</note> and ſeeke to obey him faithfullie and redely as hee commaundeth euen from the bot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tome of our hearts and ſoules, wee are vnworthy the name of his ſeruants or to continue in his bleſſed ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uice, for not euerie one that ſaith <hi>Lord Lord,</hi> ſhall in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>herit his kingdome, but hee that withall <note n="(h)" place="margin">Math. 7.21</note> obeyeth his commaundements as hee requireth.</p>
            <p>Now let vs proceede to ſpeak a little of thoſe no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table reaſons,<note place="margin">Three reaſons to mooue vs to ſerue god.</note> which <hi>Daniel</hi> here vſeth to perſwade <hi>Salomon</hi> to ſerue his God, which are three in number euerie one more forcible to moue then other.</p>
            <p>The firſt is taken from the naturall inſight, know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge and vnderſtanding of the Almightie: that hee ſearcheth all hearts, and vnderſtandeth all the ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginations of thoughts, which points beeing euer in our remembrance,<note place="margin">The firſt reaſon to ſerue God.</note> will make vs hence foorth more watchfull to looke to oar waies, both to forſake that which is ill, and faithfullye to followe that which is good: For what ſeruant (though neuer ſo bad) that hee ſerueth ſuch a wiſe maſter, as will not only call him to account, how he hath wrought and done his buſines,<note place="margin">What will make a loyterer labour</note> but will further haue ſuch a watching eye into his continuall labours, as if hee ſhould but loy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter but one houre, ſhoulde take him tardie, would not ſuch a maſter make him ſtirre his ſtumps, if hee either regarded to pleaſe him at all, or hoped in the end to be payed for his paines, how could it bee o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe?</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Why all ſhoulde ſerue God.</note>Then I beſecch you, let mee once againe exhort euerie perſon, from the higheſt to the loweſt, from the beſt to the worſte, to walke more vprightlye in their places and callings ſeing they profeſſe to ſerue that God who ſearcheth all ſecrets, and will one day call them to make account how they haue vſed or abu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſed
<pb facs="tcp:8780:27"/>
his talents.</p>
            <p>If thoſe couetous cormerants that ſcrape &amp; ſcratch this earthly pelfe togither, by hooke and crooke,<note place="margin">Why couetous men ſhould re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent.</note> right or wrong, they care not how ſo they can catche it, could reme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ber thus much, that the Lord God ſeeth all their ill dealings and will one day call them to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count for the ſame, they would not ſtil wilfully pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoke his wrath towards them by offending his maie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtie, O then let this reaſon mooue them to repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance.</p>
            <p>If thoſe carnall minded men,<note place="margin">Why drunk<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> ſhould repent.</note> that giue them ſelues to ſurfeting and drunkennes, to whordome and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleannes, would call to remembrance that the Lord God ſeeth all their waies, and will one day call them to account for the ſame, it would make them leaue all manner of filthines: O then let this reaſon &amp;c.</p>
            <p>If the wrangling Lawyers or other pettie foggers that abuſe good lawes and godly Gouernours,<note place="margin">Why wrangling lawyers ſhoulde repeat.</note> by bearing and bolſtring vp bad men and cauſes ſhould conſider thus much that the Lord God ſeeth the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedings, and will one day call them to account for the ſame, they would forſake all ſuch euil waies: O then &amp;c,</p>
            <p>If the ſeceret vndermyning vſurer,<note place="margin">Why vſurers ſhould repent.</note> and all ſuch cooſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning deceitfull craftſ-me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, ſhould wiſelye forethinke that how cloſlye ſo euer they conuey their craftines, from the eyes of good-men, yet they cannot hyde the ſame from the Lord, but hee thorowly ſeeth and ſearcheth the ſame, &amp; will one day call them to make their accounts: they would then foorth with gaue o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer ſuch wickednes: O then &amp;c.</p>
            <p>If all Church papiſts who carry to faces vnder one hood,<note place="margin">Why church-pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſts ſhould re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent.</note> ſhould meditate thus much with them ſelues that albeit they diſſemble and cloke their hippocri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie neuer ſo cunningly from the eyes of the Lord, yet
<pb facs="tcp:8780:28"/>
the God of heauen that hateth all hipocriſie he ſeeth and will ſearch the ſecrets of their conſciences, and will one day call them to account for the ſame: O then. &amp;c. And wheras <hi>Dauid</hi> ſaith the Lord ſearch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth all hearts, noating aſ well the good as the bad, of of what calling, cuntrey or condition ſoeuer <note n="(i)" place="margin">Gen. 1.26.37 Pſal. 44.9.10.11.</note> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he onely made the heart of man, let euerie chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian learne thus much therby, that in all their waies they walk ſo vprightly,<note place="margin">Why wee all ſhould repent.</note> as all their thoughts, woords and woorks may be euer framed after Gods wil: that when they ſhall lay open the ſecrets of all men, their conſciences in that day may not accuſe them.</p>
            <p>O then ſet this reaſon mooue them to repentance.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">The ſecond rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon to moue vs to ſerue God.</note>Now let vs come to the ſecond reaſon, which <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uid</hi> vſeth to make vs ſerue God, which is drawe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> from the bleſsing that ſhall enſue therof: <hi>Jf thou ſeeke God hee will be found of thee,</hi> wheerin wee haue to learne theſe two leſſons.</p>
            <p>Firſt, what it is to finde God.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>wo good points</note>Secondly, the way and meanes how we may finde him.</p>
            <p>Touching the former, (though it be ſet downe by Dauid in the latter places) yet ſeeing it is a ſpeciall reaſon to mooue vs to ſeeke God,<note place="margin">Why I place fin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding before ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king.</note> and moued in o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther places to go before as in 130. Pſalme verſe 4, where it it is ſaid, with the Lord is mercie, that hee may be feared, planting mercie before as the cauſe of true feare.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">The firſt pointe, what it is to find God.</note>I will therefore ſpeake firſte of that excellent ble<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſsing what it is to finde God, which in a woord is to finde all the treaſures in heauen and in earth, &amp; not only to fynde them, but alſo to enioy them for euer more.</p>
            <p>For when as the Lord created heauen and earth, &amp; all thinges therin for the vſe of man, to take and vſe
<pb facs="tcp:8780:28"/>
them at his will and pleaſure, yea more, to guyde and gouerne them as their ſouerain Lord when nee was falne from his firſt integritie. Then how much more doth the right vſe of them appertain vnto vs, when wee are reconcyled into Gods fauour, and deſire to ſeeke to finde the Lord Ieſus.</p>
            <p>Dooſt thou not want wit or wiſdome to guyde thy ſelf aright in the duties of thy calling,<note place="margin">Where wiſdome is to be found.</note> all the tre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures of vnderſtanding, wit or wiſdo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>e remaine in the Lord, therfore if thou finde him, thou canſt want no wiſdome.</p>
            <p>Art thou ſick, poore or any way diſtreſſed in ſoule or bodie, all health, wealth,<note place="margin">Where to finde health. &amp;c.</note> and welfare are reſident in God therfore if thou finde him thou canſt lack no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing that is good.</p>
            <p>Doe thine enemies purſue and perſecute thy ſoule, all power is the Lords in <note n="(b)" place="margin">
                  <p>Mat. 28.18. Col. 2.15.</p>
                  <p>Where to finde ſafetie againſt al enemies.</p>
               </note> heauen and in earth, he hath ſubdued ſatan, ſinne, death and damnation: therfore if thou finde him thou canſt wa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t no ſtre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gth to conquer all thine enemies, be they neuer ſo many malitious or mightie.</p>
            <p>Doth thy conſcience oppreſſe thee with the weight of thy ſinners, the Lord hath nayled them faſte vnto his croſſe <note n="(l)" place="margin">Col. 2.14.</note> and fully ſatisfied his farhers iuſtice for them, therfore if thou finde him, thy ſinnes ſhall not torment thee.</p>
            <p>Wouldeſt thou gladly haue life euerlaſting and be pertaker of the ioyes of heauen?<note place="margin">Where ſaluation is to be found.</note> Chriſt Ieſus thy ſaui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our hath purchaſed &amp; prepared heauen for thee and all his redeemed, therfore if thou finde him thou fin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſt ſaluation.</p>
            <p>Thou canſt not name any thing needful in heauen or in earth, belonging to this life or the life to come, but the ſame is in Chriſt moſt plentifully for in him (as the Scripture ſaith) all <note n="(m)" place="margin">Col. 1.19.</note> fulnes dooth dwell:
<pb facs="tcp:8780:29"/>
Therfore to finde him, is to finde all treaſures in hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen and in earth.</p>
            <p>Seeing therfore all true ioy and felicitie is ſolelye and wholely to be found in Chriſt Ieſus,<note place="margin">The 3 point how to finde God</note> and that no man can compaſſe or co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>prehend the ſame, but ſuch only (as know and finde him) let vs now come too to ſpeak of that matter which is the ſecond pointe heere to bee handled without the which (whatſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer hath been ſaid) all is in vaine and cannot profite vs.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">A fit ſimile.</note>As for example, if I knowe certainly that in ſuch a word an infinite made of money were hidde, if the owner therof would giue it vnto mee, yet if by no meanes I could finde the ſame, what ſhould the gift of ſuch a treſure profit me? if it were of value to pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaſe a kingdome nothing at all: ſo ſtandeth the caſe, betweene Chriſte and vs, Though I knowe neuer ſo well and certainly, that all kinde of treaſure is permi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent in him, and doe belong to ſuch as can finde him yet if can by no meanes finde him what ſhall the vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding heer of profit mee? nothing at all.</p>
            <p>Oh then in Gods name giue heed to that which fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loweth and lay it vp ſafely in the cofer of your harts, for then ſhall you be ſure to finde Chriſte indeed: if thou ſeek God (ſaith David) he will be fou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d of thee, ſo that all the vertue lyeth in this woord ſeeke, wher uppon aryſeth theſe two queſtions.<note place="margin">Two Queſtions.</note>
            </p>
            <list>
               <item>Firſt, where to ſeeke Chriſte.</item>
               <item>Second, how to ſeeke for him.</item>
            </list>
            <p>Touching the former, Chriſt him ſelfe will reſolue vs, who teacheth euerie one that would finde him, to <note n="(n)" place="margin">Ioh. 5, 39. Chriſte in the <gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>cripture.</note> ſearch the holy Scripture: In the ſcripture ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore Chriſt is to be found, and thoſe that would finde him, there muſt they ſeeke him</p>
            <p>For though it be true that Chriſt is in the heauens,
<pb facs="tcp:8780:29"/>
(as touching his humanitie) <note n="(o)" place="margin">Col. 3.1.</note> and that there wee muſt ſeeke him at the right hand of his father: yet whoſoeuer would know what Chriſt hath done for him to bring him to that glorie, in the Scriptures on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly there muſt they finde it.<note place="margin">Chriſts bodie <gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> heauen, his ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue in earth.</note>
            </p>
            <p>And though it may bee truelye ſaid alſo, that the Lord is preſent in his Sanctuarie amongſt the aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly of his ſeruants, <note n="(p)" place="margin">Mat<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. 13.30.</note> to direct and guyde them by his holy ſpirit, yet the way and meanes rightly to di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinguiſh betweene Gods ſanctuarye, and the ſina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>goge of Satan: is by reteyning therin the exerciſes of religion pure and vndefiled, according to the word, ſo that ſtill the ſcripture muſt be ſought vnto, being of them ſelues only ſufficient, for teaching all trueth, <note n="(q)" place="margin">2. Tim. 3.16, 17.</note> for confuting all errors, for inſtructing in all god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lines, and for reprouing all manner vice, that the man of God may be perfect in all things.</p>
            <p>Seeing by theſe prooues it plainly appeareth, that Chriſt to our comfort (as touching his offices of king <note n="(r)" place="margin">Ioh. 5.39.</note> preeſt and prophet) Is truely and effectually to be found in the Scripture.<note place="margin">2. part how to ſearch the ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures to finde Chriſte.</note>
            </p>
            <p>It followeth now to ſpeake of the latter part, how to ſearch the Scriptures that wee may finde Chriſte, which <hi>Salomon</hi> teacheth vs plainly in theſe woords: If thou ſeeke wiſdome as for ſiluer: and ſearcheſt for her, as for treaſures: then ſhalt thou vnderſtand the feare of the Lord: by wiſdome in this place, is vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood, the true knowledge of Chriſt in the ſcripture.</p>
            <p>Now then wee are to enquire, what paines &amp; tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uell all men take, that ſeeke and ſearch for ſiluer and treaſure, ſeeing this example is ſette before vs to i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitate and follow:<note place="margin">How all men la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour for ſiluer.</note> The merchant ventereth bothe goods and lyfe to come by this ſiluer, the lawyer ſpendeth his toung and ſtumps to get this ſiluer: the ſcience man toyleth his head and handes to obtaine
<pb facs="tcp:8780:30"/>
ſiluer: the poore man woorketh both day and night to earne this ſiluer: but let vs co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>e to the other point touching the digging &amp; ſearching for treaſure, which dooth more aptly expreſſe our dutie.</p>
            <p>If it bee but a moyne of copper, tyn or lead, what paine and diligence is vſed by the owner to come by the ſame, but if it prooue a veine of ſiluer or golde, Oh then how glad is the Lord of that ſoyle,<note place="margin">Oh diligence of mettall Myners.</note> how quicklye dooth hee ſet poyners on woorke, how e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerly then is the veine followed, with what care, co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage and comfort doe all men labour almoſt day and night in hope to be greatly enriched therby: all ſuch men know, as haue experience in thoſe matters, that there is no care, no paines, nor any coſte ſpared to effect their buſines, and get the ſaid treaſure. Yea albeit the vein ſinck downe very deepe and prooue moſt hard and difficult to win, yet do they not ceaſe nor ſlacken their labour, but rather adde ſo much the more diligence, in hope that their gaines doe double their paines when the moyen is once wonne: for this they hould (as a rule infallable) that the lower any mettall dooth lye in the earth,<note place="margin">The lower the mettall lyes, the better, it proues.</note> the better and more gainfull it prooues in ſubſtance.</p>
            <p>Euen ſo it is in the ſtudie of the Scriptures, the more paines and diligence thou vſeſt therin, the more increaſe of ſound knowledge, wiſdome and comfort is gotten in the end: beeing that moſte rich and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>valuable moyne wherein <note n="(s)" place="margin">Pſal. 119. Pro. 3.13.14.26. &amp; 8.18.19.</note> all the treaſures of wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome and vnderſtanding are to be found co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>teining and compredending all the holy counſells and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maundements of the Lord, ſo <note n="(t)" place="margin">Iohn. 20.31.</note> much as is neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie for our ſaluation, the eſtimate wherof is ſo ineſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mable, as our Sauiour preferreth the deare ſaluaton of one poore ſoule <note n="(v)" place="margin">Math. 16.26.</note> to all the treaſures and plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures in this world, neither can it be other wiſe, for
<pb facs="tcp:8780:30"/>
the blood of Chriſt (by which our ſinnes are purged) as the Scripture dooth witnes <note n="(x)" place="margin">1 Iohn 1.7. 1 Peet. 1.18.</note> is much more pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious then all golde and pearles.</p>
            <p>Moreouer this diuerſitie there is betweene thoſe that ſeeke for earthly treaſures, and them that ſtudie the holy Scriptures, that wheras oftentimes the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer looſſe their labour in miſsing that they ſeek for, yet there was neuer any ſince the world began that fought the Lord vnfeignedly in the holye Scripture but they found him, as the examples of all the Patri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>archs, Prophets, and Apoſtles, with all other our forefathers mentioned in Scripture from the firſt of <hi>Geneſis</hi> till the laſt of <hi>Apocal<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ps</hi> dooth plentifully wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes: o then how ought all men (of what eſtate ſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer) to ſtudie the holy Scripture?</p>
            <p>But the Maſters of moyners will obiect and ſay,<note place="margin">An obiection.</note> we can ſet others on woorke to digge mettall, and when it is found, take the gaines to our ſelues, may we not doe the like in ſearching of the ſcripture.</p>
            <p>I anſwere no,<label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſwer. </seg>
               </label> for <hi>Dauid</hi> heere telleth <hi>Salomon</hi> his ſonne that if hee would finde God, hee him ſelf muſt ſeeke him, and not paſſe it ouer vnto others, as great men commonly doe in theſe dayes: ſaying, to ſtudie the Scriptures belongeth only to men of the church, preachers and ſuch like, as though none but learned men ſhould be ſaued, for ſo they muſt needs wreſt the Lords ſpeaches, where hee willeth all that longs for life eternall <note n="(y)" place="margin">Ioh. 5.13.</note> to ſtudie the Scriptures.</p>
            <p>Let no man therfore ſaint to himſelf of what calling ſoeuer) that he can get any other way to heauen, but by the Lord Ieſus, and by him only: or that Chriſt is at all to be found their Sauiour: but as the Scripture dooth teſtifie of him, or they can poſsibly finde him therin, if them ſelues doe not ſeeke him with their whole heart, as <hi>Dauid</hi> did <note n="(a)" place="margin">Pſal. 119. Deu. 17.19. Ioh. 1.8.</note> and as all kings &amp; prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces
<pb facs="tcp:8780:31"/>
are enioyned. For as no man liuing can get anie gaines or finde any moyne of mettall or treaſure,<note place="margin">A fit ſimile</note> ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept hee take paines to open the earth, &amp; follow the veine with labour and dilligence: no more ſhall any man euer attain to find out the treaſures that are hid in Chriſt,<note place="margin">How Chriſt is to be found or</note> except he diligentlye ſtudie the Scripture and frequent holy exerciſes where the woord is pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched, then (and not before then) ſhall hee taſte and feel how ſweet the Lord is, for ſo himſelf inſtructeth vs how to finde him, ſaying, ſeeke <note n="(b)" place="margin">Mat. 7.78. Ignorance of dangerous.</note> and yee ſhall finde him: but hee neuer promiſed to be found of thoſe that ſeeke not to finde him.</p>
            <p>If wee ſhould therfore wiſelie he conſider, how many and great inconueniences doe growe through igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance of the ſcripture, then would wee more careful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lye labour day and night to be conuerſant in them. What is the cauſe why millions of thouſands where poperie is profeſſed, are ſo groſſe idolaters to fall downe and pray before ſtocks &amp; blocks, which they tearme holy Images, yet are called of the Lord and his holy prophets falſe Images <note n="(c)" place="margin">Exo. 20 4 5 Deu. 4 15 29 Ier, 51 17 18</note> lying teachers, &amp; deceiuable vanities forbidden to be vſed: but are al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>togither ignorant in Gods woord, and ſuffer them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues to be lead blyndfolde by ſuch blynde guydes <note n="(d)" place="margin">Mat. 15.14</note> as will bring them all to fall in the ditch.</p>
            <p>What is the cauſe why ſo many hundreths, teare and blaſpheme the holy name of God by ſwearing and forſwearing without any cauſe, but that they are ignoraunt of the Scripture, which threatneth great iudgeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts <note n="(e)" place="margin">3. Command. Zechas 5 2 3 4</note> againſt ſuch vile wretches.</p>
            <p>What is the cauſe why ſo many perſons wilfully pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phane the Lords holy Saboths, in proſecuting on that day their ordinarie accouſtomed cauſes &amp; pleaſures, but they haue not peruſed the ſcripture, which plain<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly denounceth <note n="(f)" place="margin">4 Commaund. Exo. 31 14</note> great iudgements againſt him.</p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:8780:31"/>What is the cauſe ſo many wickedly riſe and rebell againſt their owne ſouerainge <note n="(g)" place="margin">Rom. 13 16</note> and ſuperiours but they are ignorant in the ſcriptures, which threatneth great iudgements againſt ſuch wicked wretches.</p>
            <p>What is the cauſe that amongſt all callings ſome are malitious, ſome vitious perſons, ſome drunkerds, ſome deceitfull perſons, ſome couetous, ſome con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentious perſons but that they knowe not the holy Sctipture, which ptonounceth damnation <note n="(h)" place="margin">1 Cor. 6 9 <gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Gal. 517 <gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>0 <gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> to all ſuch wicked woorkers.</p>
            <p>I wiſh with all my heart, that theſe my examples of ſo great inconueniences continuallye accompaning the ignorance of the Scriptures, may mooue all per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons to take greater pleaſure in reading of Gods woord, eſpecially ſeeing ſo exceeding benefit is pro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>miſed to thoſe that delight therin, &amp; labour to frame their liues thereafter as hath been declared.</p>
            <p>The manner and way to ſearch the holy ſcripture without doubt or daunger to fall into errors, is to read the ſame with an humble ſpirit, as Chriſt ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth him ſelfe an <note n="(i)" place="margin">Mat. 11.29</note> example) to marke diligentlie that goeth before and followeth after, and to what end the ſame tendeth, conferring one place with an other, and rightly diſtinguiſhing betweene allego<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, parables and plain ſpeaches,<note place="margin">How to read the ſcripture with proffit.</note> calling continually on the Lord by prayer for his grace and holy ſpirit: then ſhall we know the ſecrets <note n="(k)" place="margin">Pſal. 25.9.</note> of the Lord, then wherunto if you adde a perfect heart and a willing minde, to refourme your religion and life therafter, ſhall you abound in the knowledge of the Lord, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſhall his word be moſt ſweet vnto your ſoules,<note place="margin">The benefit of reading the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſcripture to ſerue God ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after.</note> then wil you prefer the ſame to all wordly pleaſures, then ſhall the power therof ſubdue all ſin in you, then wil Gods ſpirit woork a chaunge in you, then ſhall both your life &amp; religion pleaſe God, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſhall you indeed finde the Lord Ieſus, then ſhall you proſper in all his waies,
<pb facs="tcp:8780:32"/>
then will he protect you againſt all your enemies, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> will he preſerue you in all extremities, then will hee comfort you in the houre of death and then will hee bring you to his ioyes eternall, which is the cheife bleſsing of all other bleſsings. It followeth now to ſpeake of the laſt reaſon which <hi>Dauid</hi> vſeth to vrge vs to ſerue God, if the former ſhould faile, drawen wholely from the iudgements of God againſt ſuch as contemne the ſame,<note place="margin">The third reaſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to mooue vs to ſerue God.</note> which may well be tearmed the whip-cord reaſon to cauſe and compell vs to ſerue the Lord, or els nothing will preuaile, which is only thus much, <hi>Jf thou for ſake God hee will caſt theee of for euer.</hi>
               <note place="margin">The whip-cord reaſon.</note> As if <hi>Dauid</hi> ſhould haue ſaide vnto <hi>Salomon,</hi> of all the ſonnes that God hath giuen mee, I haue euer been moſte carefull of thee (<hi>o Salomon) to knowe and ſerue God</hi> becauſe I foreknew thou ſhouldſt be a king to guide this great people acording to his wil: I haue plainly tolde the way and manner how, <hi>with a perfect heart and a willing minde</hi>: I haue ſhewed thee further two forcible reaſons to mooue thee therunto: The firſt drawen from the nature of God, that he ſeeth &amp; ſearcheth all mens hearts and vnderſtandeth all their ſecrets: the other taken from that exceeding bleſsing which ſhall inſue the ſeruice of god: <hi>if thou ſeek him he will be found of thee</hi>: and in finding him, thou findeſt all treaſures in heauen &amp; in earth: Now if neither of theſe aleadged reaſons, nor any of my former perſwa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions, can cauſe thee to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tinue in the ſeruice of God yet if thou haue any care at all to eſcape hell &amp; come vnto heauen, ſee thou ſeeke and ſerue the Lord God truely according to his word, otherwiſe I proteſt be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore his glorious preſence and heere before all my E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtates, that if thou forſake him, he will caſt thee off for euer, both from being king, &amp; out of his fauour, which thou ſhalt be ſure one day to finde: o then let this reaſon preuaile, to cauſe thee ſerue God faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully.</p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:8780:32"/>But to make this reaſon a little more playne,<note place="margin">Two poin<gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> let vs conſider of theſe two points. Firſt, what it is to forſake God, and ſecondly who they are that forſake him: be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore we come to ſpeake of their iudgement.<note place="margin">Vnbeliefe is to forſake God.</note> Touching the former, To forſake God, as the Apoſtle noteth to the Hebrues, is to haue an euill and vnbeleeuing heart. Heb. 3.12. Which importeth firſt, they muſt be belee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers, elſe how can it be truly ſayde,<note place="margin">More plainly reuealed.</note> They departe from that which they neuer had: ſo that of neceſsitie this is to forſake God, a reuolting from that ſound faith and religion of the goſpel, which the partie once hath pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſed.</p>
            <p>Another kinde of forſaking God, Salomon deſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beth in the firſt of his Prouerbes, which is wilfully to hate the knowledge of God, or to bee guided after his word. Whome the Church tearmeth further,<note place="margin">Pro. 22 31</note> ſuch as mock Gods ordinances, which ſort of ſinners alſo the Lord will reiect.</p>
            <p>Now then let vs come to the ſecond point; to exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine by theſe rules,<note place="margin">who they are that for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſake God.</note> who they are in deed that forſake God, that is to ſaie, all ſuch as willingly reuolt from that faith of Chriſts holy Goſpel which they once pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſed; or wilfully refuſe to conforme or reforme their liues thereafter, and yet profeſſe the ſame.</p>
            <p>Theſe definitions of forſaking God, which are groun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded on his word, doth lay open the eſtate of two ſortes of people to be moſt dangerous. The one is,<note place="margin">In what e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtate the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uolters from the Goſpell are Math, 15, 6</note> of all ſuch Papiſts, and other reuolters of what ſtate ſo ouer, who before time haue openly profeſſed and proteſted the religion of the Goſpell, and now are Apoſtates, imbra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing poperie, and their own inuentions in Gods wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, flatly forbidden by his holy word.<note place="margin">In what e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtate carnall Goſpellers are.</note> The other ſort is, of ſuch as profeſſe the truth of religion according to the Goſpell in their ſpeeches, but refuſe vtterly to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forme their liues thereafter, and ſo denie the power thereof to worke in their harts, as the Apoſtle noteth
<pb facs="tcp:8780:33"/>
Rom. 1.18.31. Of which curſed companie are all ſuch as we call carnall goſpellers, of what ſort ſo euer.</p>
            <p>If al profeſſors within this realme of England ſhould examine their liues without partialitie, whether the ſame agree in all points with that holy goſpel of Chriſt Ieſus, whereof we make ſo fayre proteſtations, I doubt many of vs, yea many thouſands, ſhall bee found ſuch as forſake God, our liues &amp; conuerſation are ſo abho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minabl<gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>his ſ<gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ght. For, howe many of vs haue often heard patched, and read in Gods word, That vſury and extortion, pride and oppreſsion, whooredome and dronkenneſſe, lying and ſwearing, ſlandering &amp; back<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>biting, mallice and hatred, couetouſneſſe and conten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, with all other groſſe ſinnes, are flatly forbidden by the word of God, vpon <note n="(n)" place="margin">2. Cor, 9, 10. Gal. 5.19 20, 11.</note> paine of damnation, and yet doo wallowe therein. I do appeale to euerie mans conſcience, with this caueat, that whoſoeuer doth feel himſelfe guiltie in anie of them, hee ſeeke to forſake them,<note place="margin">Who ſo re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pents not, muſt needes forſake God.</note> &amp; to ſerue God better, leaſt he be found amongſt that curſed companie of ſuch wicked wretches as for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſake the Lorde God, and then muſt his iudgementes needs ceaze vpon them. Which now followeth ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing to be ſpoken of.</p>
            <p>Dauid ſaith to Salomon, If thou forſake God, he wil caſt thee off for euer. Now to be caſt off for euer, what is it elſe but to looſe the fauour of God in this world,<note place="margin">The moſt fearful iudg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nts of ſuch as forſake God.</note> and eternal felicitie in the world to come, and not that onely, but to be caſt into endleſſe torments of ſoule &amp; bodie when this life is ended: yea, for the moſt part, as ſuch perſons haue not anie regard to ſerue God in this world: ſo he maketh them often ſubiect to his iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments in this life.</p>
            <p>As for example, the Apoſtle ſaith, that as they regar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded not to know and ſerue God, ſo he gaue them vp in to reprobate windes. Rom. 1.28. to doo thoſe thinges that were not conuenient, whoſe end is damnation,
<pb facs="tcp:8780:33"/>
2. The. 1.6.9 which ſhal neither haue eaſe nor ending.</p>
            <p>But to produce ſome fearefull examples of ſuch as refuſed either to know God in his goſpel, or to reforme their liues thereafter, that ſuch as delight in the ſame wicked waies, may either repent, or looke for like iudg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Wilfull pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumption pu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>niſhed in A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam &amp; Eue.</note>Adam and Eue our originall parents, being planted in paradiſe, a place of all pleaſure <gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hey woulde needes follow their owne wicked will againſt the forbidden commandement of God. But what became of them? both they and we their wofull poſteritie were baniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed paradiſe, a place of pleaſure,<note place="margin">Gen, 3, 23</note> and are now ſubiects to all kinde of miſerie of ſoule &amp; bodie: a fearefull exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple to all ſelfe-willed diſcontented perſons, O then let this reaſon compell vs to repent!</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Wilful mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der puniſhed in Kaine. Gen 4, 1<gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note>Kaine the firſt of Adam, he not regarding the Lords commandement, did wilfully murther Abel his brother; but what became of him? both he and all his of-ſpring became vagabonds and bondmen: a feare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful example to al malitious perſons, O then let this, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Wilful wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhippers pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed. Leu. 10, 1, 2</note>Nadab and Abihu, they wold needs offer ſtrange fire vnto God, contrarie to his expreſſe commandement, but what became of them? themſelues wer as ſtrange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly conſumed with fire (s) a dreadfull example to all worſhippers againſt Gods word, O then, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Diſobedie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce puniſhed. Numb, 16 31, 32</note>Corah, Dathan, and Abiram, they would not be obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dient to Moſes their gouernor, as the Lord had com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded: but what became of them, the earth did o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen (t) and ſwallow them vp quicke, a fearefull exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple to all rebellious perſons againſt their lawfull magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrates, O then let vs, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Prophanne puniſhed. Gen, 7, 21</note>The people in Noahs time, were giuen generally to all prophanenes, and would not repent at Gods fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warning: but what became of them? they were all o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerwhelmed in the generall deluge: a terrible exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple to all prophane perſons, O then let, ctc.</p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:8780:34" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <note place="margin">Vncleannes puniſhed.</note> The inceſtuous Sodomites, they would needs pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecute their abhominations agaynſt the good coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſell of Lot their neighbor:<note place="margin">Gen, 19, 24</note> but what became of them, they were al conſumed with the ſtinking fire of brim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtone from heauen, a feareful example to all licentious perſons, O then let, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">
                  <p>Couetouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes puniſhed 1, King, 21, 9 <hi>1, 19,</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>2, King, 6, 33 36,</p>
               </note>Iezabel the Queene did wring N<gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>boths vineyard by violence from him, and cauſed him to be killed, ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſly contrarie to the eight co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mandement: but what became of her? the dogges did afterwards cate vp her fleſh: a terrible example to all bloudie couetous op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſors. O then let vs, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Treaſon pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed 2, Sam. 17, 23 Math, 27.25</note>Ahitophel and Iudas would needs betray their owne ſoueraigne Lords againſt Gods commandement, and their own conſciences: but what became of them? they both became deſperate and hanged themſelues: a fear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full example to all traitors. O then let vs, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Vnmerciful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe puni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed. Luke 6, 3, 6, Luke 16, 19, 20.31</note>Diues the rich man would not ſhew mercie to poore Lazarus lying at his gates, againſt Chriſts commaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dement: but what became of him? he was himſelf be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reft of all mercie, and caſt into hell: a terrible example to all mercileſſe people. O then let vs, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Diſſemblers puniſhed Act, 2, 12</note>Ananias and Saphira did wilfully diſſemble againſt their owne conſciences: but what became of them? they were both arreſted with ſodaine death: a feareful example to all diſſembling perſons. O then, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Perſecutours puniſhed Act, 12, 23</note>Herod the king was a bloudie perſecuter of poore Chriſtians: but what became of him? he was miſerably eaten and conſumed with wormes: a terrible example for all perſecutors, O then let, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Malitiouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes puniſhed</note>The malitious Iewes would need<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> of enuie put Chriſt to death: but what became of them? they are now be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come vagabonds throughout the world, and haue no Countrie of their owne to reſt in: a fearefull example for all enuious perſons, O then let, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>The Angels in heauen did wittingly tranſgreſſe
<pb facs="tcp:8780:34"/>
Gods holy commandementes,<note place="margin">Pride puni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed 2, Pet, 2, 4 Iude 6</note> &amp; through pride rebel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led: but what became of them? they were caſt out of heauen and became deuils in hell: a fearefull example to proud perſons. O then, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>Our ſauiour Ieſus the God of all glorie, would needs take vpon him our earthly nature, to aunſwere and ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfie the iuſtice of his father for all our iniquities: but what became of him?<note place="margin">Chriſt Ieſus puniſhed for vs. Luk 1, 74, 75</note> Did he not vndergoe the paines of hell for euer, and all extreame torments of ſoule and bodie, to deliuer vs from hell and reſtore vs to heauen, that in the meane time whileſt we liue in this worlde, we ſhould truly ſerue him in holynes &amp; righteouſnes.</p>
            <p>And ſhall we once dreame or imagine ſo groſly, that God will ſpare vs co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tinuing in ſin, that ſpared not his owne moſt deare and only ſonne, the verie iewel of heauen and earth,<note place="margin">Will GOD puniſh his ſonne Chriſt and ſpare vs continuing in ſinne</note> being cleane and vnſpotted of anie ſinne, when he dyd ſeeke in loue to pacifie his fathers wrath for our ſinnes: O intollerable madneſſe, did the Lord puniſh Adam in paradiſe, and the Angels in hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen when they diſobeied, and ſhal we ſcape ſcot-free? No, no it will not bee. O then, if neither the watching prouidence of the Almightie can prouoke vs, nor his exceeding mercies can allure vs, yet if wee will not ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proue our ſelues reprobates, let this forcible reaſon of Gods fearefull iudgementes againſt ſinne and ſinners compel vs to repentance, that is, euen forth with to for take our euill wayes, and followe Gods lawes with a perfect heart and a willing minde, ſo as wee may beſt pleaſe him, then ſhall he ſtill preſerue vs in this world, and reſerue vs after for his ioy eternall, Amen in Chriſt Ieſus.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="prayer">
            <pb facs="tcp:8780:35" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>A briefe praier of the foreſayd Text.</head>
            <p>O Lord our God &amp; heauenly father, how much are we beholding to thine eternal goodneſſe, for thy manifolde fauours extended vpon vs, namely, for ſending thy ſonne to redeeme vs, his ſpirit to comfort vs, and his worde to direct vs, both in our religion &amp; conuerſation, ſo as we may beſt pleaſe thee and profit thy Church: All honour and praiſe be giuen to thee therefore for euermore in Ieſus Chriſt, Amen. And ſeeing thy moſt holy word doth chifly teach vs to know &amp; ſerue then as thou requireſt, O bleſſed Father, inſtruct vs firſt to know thee what thou haſt done for vs; when we were not, to make vs after thine owne I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage: when we were loſt, to redeeme vs by the preci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous bloud of thy moſt deare ſonne Ieſus: and though we ſtill be ſinfull, to ſend thy holy ſpirit into our harts, dayly more and more to ſanctifie vs: O giue vs grace, that we may euer ſerue thee as thy worde teacheth vs, with a perfect heart and a willing <gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>inde<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: and becauſe wee are forgetfull of our dueties, make vs mindfull to thinke of thoſe three reaſons, which thy word preſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beth to drawe vs thereunto. The firſt, that thou ſeeſt vs and ſearcheſt all ſecrets. The next, that if we ſeke thee, thou wilt be found of vs, whereby we are ſure to finde all things needfull. The third, that if we forſake thee, and follow not thy lawes, thou wilt forſake vs and caſt vs off for euer. O moſt deare Father, let all theſe three reaſons be euermore before our eies, that the firſt may moue vs, the ſecond perſwade vs, and the third compel vs to ſpeedie repentance. If the ſharpe in-ſight of thy all-ſeeing nature cannot moue vs, let the vnderſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of thine eternall goodneſſe drawe vs there<gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nto: If thy euerlaſting goodnes cannot drawe vs, yet let thoſe fearefull iudgements which thy word threatneth, and heretofore hath fallen vpon the wicked, compell vs to ſeeke thee, by forſaking all our ſinnes, and following
<pb facs="tcp:8780:35" rendition="simple:additions"/>
thy lawes, with all our hearts and ſoules, that ſo wee may pleaſe thee, euerie daie more and more whilſt we do liue in this wretched worlde, that when this life is ended, we may be inheritors of thy glory endleſie, ther<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>to praiſe thy holy name for euermore, Amen. O bleſſed Father, ſaue thy Church vniuerſall, our Queene &amp; this realme, giue thy Goſpell and the gouernment thereof a more free paſſage in all kingdomes and countryes, namely in England; that as the rod of Aaron deuoured and conſumed al the <gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ods of the Sorcerers and Inchan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of Egypt: ſo the preaching Miniſterie of thy bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed Goſpel, may beate downe and deſtroy all falſe, fai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, and idolatrous opinions, ſects, ſciſmes, and here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſies, contrarie thereunto, in all kingdomes &amp; countries (namely in England) that Sion may reioyce, and Iſrael may be glad, our Queene, her Counſell, and all eſtates may triumph, when ſatan and ſinne are dayly ſubdued, and Chriſt by his ordinances raigne in his Church, and his Goſpel floriſh in all kingdomes (eſpecially in Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land) that we may all know it and ſerue him thereafter, to the eternall praiſe of his great name of mercie, and our euerlaſting comfort in Chriſt, vnto whoſe moſt bleſſed Maieſtie, with thee O father Almightie, &amp; the bleſſed ſpirit of truth, three perſons in one godhead, be aſcribed all honor, glorie, power, praiſe, and dominion from all his creatures in heauen and in earth, more ſpecially from mankind, and moſt of all from his rede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med, now and euer.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
